<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="Axis_Plotting" label="9">
  <title>Axis Plotting</title>

  <xi:include href="../phrases/chapterinfo_mod.xml"
              xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

  <section id="Axis_Introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para><productname>Magics</productname> axis facilities allow users to plot horizontal
    and vertical axes on non-geographical plots. These facilities include axis labelling, axis title plotting and
    subdivision of axes with ticks. There is also a facility for plotting automatic
    date/time axes.</para>

    <para>Parameters exist which give the user control over all aspects of axis plotting,
    e.g. position, orientation, colour, thickness etc. Axis plotting is achieved by
    calling the action routine <function>PAXIS</function>, which draws one axis each
    time it is called. Any axis parameters required must be set before <function>PAXIS</function>
    is called. <function>PAXIS</function> may be called as often as it is needed. If more than one axis is to be drawn with the same axis orientation and
    position, users should ensure that there is sufficient room between the subpage
    and page frame lines.</para>

    <para>Axis plotting is based on the <productname>Magics</productname> subpage. 
    It is necessary to ensure that the dimensions of the subpage are
    set before <function>PAXIS</function> is called, as the requested axis will be
    drawn on one of the subpage frame lines. This means that the parameters
    <parameter>SUBPAGE_X_LENGTH</parameter> and <parameter>SUBPAGE_Y_LENGTH</parameter>
    should be set to the required values and <parameter>SUBPAGE_MAP_PROJECTION</parameter>
    should be set to '<code>CARTESIAN</code>'.
    Horizontal axes are always plotted along the bottom or top line of the subpage frame.
    Vertical axes are plotted along the left or right side of the subpage frame.</para>

    <para>The axes, which may be regular, logarithmic or user-defined, may be subdivided
    with tick marks. Further subdivision between tick marks, i.e. minor ticks, is also
    possible. Grid lines, i.e. lines joining corresponding tick marks, may be plotted.
    Ticks may be labelled either on the tick marks or between tick marks.</para>

    <para><productname>Magics</productname> parameters exist to control all aspects of axis drawing.
    These parameters start with the prefix <parameter>AXIS</parameter>, e.g.
    <parameter>AXIS_LINE_THICKNESS</parameter>.</para>

    <para>An axis consists of seven different parts and the drawing of each part can be turned on or off.
    The parts are: line, title, tip title, ticks, minor ticks, tick labels and grid. The line, ticks,
    tick labels and title are on by default. The grid, minor ticks and tip title are off by default.
    </para>

    <para>Axes may be annotated in two ways, one called the axis title and the other called
    the <firstterm>axis tip title</firstterm>. The axis title is centred on the axis and
    the tip title is plotted at the end of the axis. The tip title would normally be
    used as a unit specification. The default text string for the title and tip title are blank.
    </para>

 </section>


  <section id="Axis_Positioning">
    <title>Axis Positioning</title>

    <para>Axes may be drawn on any of the subpage frame lines. This is controlled by the parameter
    <parameter>AXIS_ORIENTATION</parameter> which may be set to
    '<code>HORIZONTAL</code>' (X-axis) or '<code>VERTICAL</code>' (Y-axis), the default being
    '<code>HORIZONTAL</code>' .</para>

    <para>The position of an axis is controlled by the parameter
    <parameter>AXIS_POSITION</parameter>. For the x-axis it can take one of the
    values '<code>BOTTOM</code>' or '<code>TOP</code>' and for the y-axis the values
    '<code>LEFT</code>' or '<code>RIGHT</code>' may be used.</para>
    
    <para>An axis is normally drawn on one of the subpage frames. However if
    <function>PAXIS</function> is called more than once with the same
    <parameter>AXIS_POSITION</parameter> value, each subsequent axis will be drawn between
    the previously drawn axis and the page frame, if there is sufficient room available.
    For example two calls with <parameter>AXIS_POSITION</parameter> set to '<code>RIGHT</code>'
    will draw the first axis on the right-hand subpage frame, and the second axis to
    the right of the first one, if there is room between the subpage and page.</para>
    
    <para>It is possible to draw the lines of an axis in any position and not just at
    the bottom/top/left/right of the axis. This is achieved by setting the parameter
    <parameter>AXIS_POSITION</parameter> to '<code>AUTOMATIC</code>' and the
    parameter <parameter>AXIS_LINE_POSITION</parameter> to the required position.
    The position of the line should be given in centimetres from the lower left hand
    corner of the subpage. <parameter>AXIS_LINE_POSITION</parameter> may be used for
    both the X and Y axes, depending on the value set in the parameter
    <parameter>AXIS_ORIENTATION</parameter> (<code>HORIZONTAL</code> or <code>VERTICAL</code>).
    It is possible to plot ticks, minor ticks, titles etc on
    <code>POSITIONAL</code> axes. However, users should be aware that the ticks etc
    will only be plotted on the left side of vertical lines and on the bottom side
    of horizontal lines.</para>
    
    <para>There is no limit to the number of times <function>PAXIS</function> may be called,
    even with the same <parameter>AXIS_POSITION</parameter>, as long as there is sufficient
    room. When there is insufficient room for the axis, an error message is generated
    and the axis is not drawn.</para>

    <para>The parameter <parameter>AXIS_LINE</parameter> controls whether the axis
    line is actually drawn or not. The default value is '<code>ON</code>' and it
    should be set to '<code>OFF</code>' if the line is not required.</para>
  </section>


  <section id="Axis_Line">
    <title>Axis Line styling</title>

    <para>The colour and thickness of the axis may be set by using the parameters
    <parameter>AXIS_LINE_COLOUR</parameter> and <parameter>AXIS_LINE_THICKNESS</parameter>.
    The default colour of the axis line is the colour of the subpage frame,
    i.e. <parameter>SUBPAGE_FRAME_COLOUR</parameter>, and the default thickness is
    <code>2</code>.</para>

  <section id="Axis_Grid_Lines">
    <title>Axis Grid Lines</title>

    <para>Grid lines may be drawn from every tick by setting the parameter
    <parameter>AXIS_GRID</parameter> to '<code>ON</code>' . The colour, thickness
    and line style of grid lines may be controlled with the parameters
    <parameter>AXIS_GRID_COLOUR</parameter>, <parameter>AXIS_GRID_THICKNESS</parameter>
    and <parameter>AXIS_GRID_LINE_STYLE</parameter>. The default values for
    these parameters are '<code>YELLOW</code>', <code>1</code> and '<code>SOLID</code>'
    respectively. Axis grids will always be drawn within the subpage even if
    the axis itself is outside the subpage.</para>
    
  </section>

  <section id="Axis_Ticks">
    <title>Axis Ticks</title>

    <para>Axis ticks are tick marks showing the subdivision of an axis. Users may control
    the drawing of tick marks by setting the parameter <parameter>AXIS_TICK</parameter>
    to '<code>ON</code>' or '<code>OFF</code>', the default being '<code>ON</code>'.</para>
    
    <para>The axis tick attributes colour, size and thickness are controlled by the
    parameters <parameter>AXIS_TICK_COLOUR</parameter>, <parameter>AXIS_TICK_SIZE</parameter>
    and <parameter>AXIS_TICK_THICKNESS</parameter>.</para>
    
    <!-- Insert diagram here? -->

    <para>An axis can be defined in four different ways with the <parameter>AXIS_TYPE</parameter>
    values '<code>REGULAR</code>' (the default), '<code>LOGARITHMIC</code>',
    '<code>POSITION_LIST</code>' and '<code>DATE</code>'.</para>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>
        <para>The '<code>REGULAR</code>' type is a regular axis defined by a first and a
        last value. The spacing of the ticks may be controlled by the user by setting
        <parameter>AXIS_TICK_INTERVAL</parameter> to the required interval.
        If not set by the user, <productname>Magics</productname> will select an
        interval that gives about 8 tick marks.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The '<code>POSITION_LIST</code>' type may be a regular or irregular axis
        with the positions of the ticks specified by the user. Tick positions are
        measured from the starting point of the axis, i.e. from the left side for
        horizontal axes and from the bottom for vertical axes. They should be passed
        to <productname>Magics</productname> in a real array as follows:
        </para>

        <programlisting>    CALL <function>PSET1R</function>('<parameter>AXIS_TICK_POSITION_LIST</parameter>',PLIST,N)</programlisting>

        <para>where <code>PLIST</code> is a real array of size <code>N</code> holding the tick positions.</para>

        <para>Normally the positions of the ticks for <parameter>POSITION_LIST</parameter> are specified
        in centimetres but can be given in axis (or user) units by setting the parameter
        <parameter>AXIS_TICK_LABEL_UNITS</parameter> to '<code>USER</code>' , the default being
        '<code>CM</code>'. In this case <productname>Magics</productname> will assume that the positions
        of the ticks in <parameter>AXIS_TICK_POSITION_LIST</parameter> are in axis units
        and will calculate the actual positions on the axis.</para>

        'DATE' is a date/time axis and is fully described in Date/Time Axis Plotting

      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>'<code>DATE</code>' is a date/time axis and is fully described in the following section.
        </para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

    

    <section id="Axis_Minor_ticks">
        <title>Axis Minor Ticks</title>

        <para>Minor tick marks are smaller than, and plotted between, tick marks.
        They may be obtained by setting <parameter>AXIS_MINOR_TICK</parameter> to
        '<code>ON</code>' and setting <parameter>AXIS_MINOR_TICK_COUNT</parameter>
        to an integer specifying the number of minor tick marks desired between
        two ticks. The default values for <parameter>AXIS_MINOR_TICK</parameter>
        and <parameter>AXIS_MINOR_TICK_COUNT</parameter> are '<code>OFF</code>' and 1,
        respectively.</para>
        
        <para>The colour, size and thickness of minor ticks may be controlled by
        setting the parameters <parameter>AXIS_MINOR_TICK_COLOUR</parameter>,
        <parameter>AXIS_MINOR_TICK_SIZE</parameter> and <parameter>AXIS_MINOR_TICK_THICKNESS</parameter>.
        </para>

    </section>

  </section>


   <section id="Axis_Spacing">
    <title>Spacing Control of Axis Ticks, Minor Ticks, Grid Lines</title>

    <para>In order to achieve good quality axis plotting without cluttering,
    it is important that ticks, minor ticks and grid lines do not come too close
    to each other. One parameter controls this: <parameter>AXIS_MINOR_TICK_MIN_GAP</parameter>.
    Using this parameter, the user may specify the smallest acceptable gap
    between ticks etc. The default value is 0.05cm . Note that the same parameter
    controls the three different features.</para>
    
   </section>
</section>



  <section id="Axis_Labels">
    <title>Axis Labels</title>

    <para>Labelling of axes consists of two different types; text labelling and unit labelling.</para>


    <section id="Axis_Text_Labels">
        <title>Text Labels</title>

        <para>There are two different types of text labelling, labelling of the axis itself,
        called the title text, and labelling of the end of an axis, called the tip title text
        <!--(see Diagram IX-1)-->.</para>
        
        <para>A title text may be plotted by setting the <parameter>AXIS_TITLE_TEXT</parameter>
        to the text required, the default is a blank text string. The parameter
        <parameter>AXIS_TITLE</parameter> should be set to '<code>ON</code>' which is
        the default. It should be set to '<code>OFF</code>' if no title text is required.
        Likewise, a tip title text may be plotted by setting <parameter>AXIS_TIP_TITLE_TEXT</parameter>
        to the text required and setting <parameter>AXIS_TIP_TITLE</parameter> to '<code>ON</code>',
        which is the default.</para>
        



        <para>The title text is always centre justified but the orientation of the text
        may be altered with the parameter <parameter>AXIS_TITLE_ORIENTATION</parameter>.
        The three valid values for this parameter are '<code>PARALLEL</code>'
        (the default), '<code>HORIZONTAL</code>' and '<code>VERTICAL</code>'. The
        orientation of the tip title text is controlled by the parameter
        <parameter>AXIS_TIP_TITLE_ORIENTATION</parameter>. Valid values are
        '<code>PARALLEL</code>', '<code>HORIZONTAL</code>' (the default) and
        '<code>VERTICAL</code>'.</para>


        <para>Parameters exist to control the colour, height and quality of the title
        text and the tip title text, e.g. <parameter>AXIS_TITLE_COLOUR</parameter>,
        <parameter>AXIS_TIP_TITLE_QUALITY</parameter> .</para>
    </section>

    <section id="Axis_Unit_Labels">
        <title>Unit Labels</title>

        <para>Unit labelling is actually the labelling of the axis ticks. This is
        controlled by the parameter <parameter>AXIS_TICK_LABEL</parameter> which
        may be set to '<code>ON</code>' or '<code>OFF</code>', the default being
        '<code>ON</code>'.</para>

        <para>Parameters exist to control the height, quality and colour of the
        tick labels, e.g.</para>
        
        <programlisting>    CALL <function>PSETC</function>('<parameter>AXIS_TICK_LABEL_COLOUR</parameter>','BLUE')</programlisting>
        
        <para>The format of the tick label may be specified by setting the parameter
        <parameter>AXIS_TICK_LABEL_FORMAT</parameter>, the default being
        '<code>(AUTOMATIC)</code>' .</para>



        <para>Tick labels can be '<code>HORIZONTAL</code>' (default) or '<code>VERTICAL</code>'
        and this is controlled by the parameter <parameter>AXIS_TICK_LABEL_ORIENTATION</parameter>.
        The user has control over the position of the tick label, by setting the
        parameter <parameter>AXIS_TICK_LABEL_POSITION</parameter>.</para>


        <para>The default position '<code>ON_TICK</code>' centres the value around
        the tick mark. The '<code>INTER_TICK</code>' position shifts all tick labels
        to the right, centring them between two tick marks. For example, the first
        tick label will be drawn between the first and the second tick.</para>


        <para>It is also possible to suppress printing of first and/or last tick label
        which is sometimes useful for space reasons. This may be achieved by setting
        the parameters <parameter>AXIS_TICK_LABEL_FIRST</parameter> and
        <parameter>AXIS_TICK_LABEL_LAST</parameter> respectively. The default value
        for both is '<code>ON</code>', which means that the first and last tick labels
        will be plotted.</para>

        <para>The parameter <parameter>AXIS_TICK_LABEL_TYPE</parameter> enables the
        user to specify the type of tick labels to be plotted, e.g.
        '<code>LABEL_LIST</code>', '<code>NUMBER</code>', '<code>LATITUDE</code>' and
        '<code>LONGITUDE</code>'. The default tick label type depends on the value
        set in <parameter>AXIS_TYPE</parameter> which may be '<code>REGULAR</code>',
        '<code>LOGARITHMIC</code>' or '<code>POSITION_LIST</code>'. For 
        '<code>REGULAR</code>' and 'LOGARITHMIC', the user may specify any of the
        valid values for <parameter>AXIS_TICK_LABEL_TYPE</parameter> and the default
        value in these two cases is '<code>NUMBER</code>'. However, if
        <parameter>AXIS_TYPE</parameter> is set to '<code>POSITION_LIST</code>' then
        '<code>LABEL_LIST</code>' is the only value allowed for
        <parameter>AXIS_TICK_LABEL_TYPE</parameter>.</para>

        <para>User defined tick labels should be passed to <productname>Magics</productname>
        in a character type array as follows:</para>

        <programlisting>    CALL <function>PSET1C</function>('<parameter>AXIS_TICK_LABEL_LIST</parameter>',TLIST,M)</programlisting>

        <para>where <code>TLIST</code> is an array of dimension <code>M</code>.
        The nth element of the array will be the label of the nth tick mark.
        If some of the ticks are to be unlabelled, the appropriate elements of the
        array should be set blank.</para>

        <para>Label types '<code>NUMBER</code>', '<code>LATITUDE</code>' and
        '<code>LONGITUDE</code>' produce numeric values calculated from the first
        axis value and the tick interval. The special cases, '<code>LATITUDE</code>'
        and '<code>LONGITUDE</code>', plot the number with a degree sign and the
        direction (N/S/E/W).</para>

        <para>It is possible to suppress the labelling of selected ticks using the 
        parameter <parameter>AXIS_TICK_LABEL_FREQUENCY</parameter>. If set to n,
        only every nth tick mark will be labelled.</para>

        <para>Logarithmic axes are labelled only at the cycle end points
        (i.e. ..,0.1,1,10,..). However if no endpoint exists (e.g. 2 to 9)
        all ticks are labelled. If there is only one endpoint it is labelled
        together with the first and the last ticks.</para>

    </section>

    
  </section>  <!-- id="Axis_Labels" -->





  <section id="Axis_Date_Time">
    <title>Date/Time Axis Plotting</title>

    <para>There are facilities for plotting an automatic date/time axis in
    <productname>Magics</productname>. The parameter <parameter>AXIS_TYPE</parameter>
    should be set to '<code>DATE</code>' when a date/time axis is required and the
    parameter <parameter>AXIS_DATE_TYPE</parameter> should be set to indicate the type
    of date/time axis required. Following is a description of how to use the date/time
    axis facilities.</para>

    <section id="AXIS_DATE_TYPE">
        <title>AXIS_DATE_TYPE</title>

        <para>The parameter <parameter>AXIS_DATE_TYPE</parameter> allows the user to
        determine which type of axis is to be drawn. Valid values are '<code>HOURS</code>',
        '<code>DAYS</code>', '<code>MONTHS</code>' and '<code>YEARS</code>'.
        The value set will determine the axis units for a date/time axis and will
        indicate that the user requests <productname>Magics</productname> to label the
        major tick marks on the current axis with date/time and that the text of the
        labels to be plotted at ticks etc be calculated by <productname>Magics</productname>.</para>

        <para>For <code>HOURS</code>, <code>DAYS</code>, <code>MONTHS</code> and <code>YEARS</code>,
        the parameters <parameter>AXIS_DATE_MIN_VALUE</parameter>,
        <parameter>AXIS_DATE_MAX_VALUE</parameter> and <parameter>AXIS_TICK_INTERVAL</parameter>
        will enable <productname>Magics</productname> to calculate the number of
        days/months/years to be plotted on the axis. <parameter>AXIS_DATE_MIN_VALUE</parameter>
        should be set to the starting date required with the format
        YYYY-MM-DD HH:mm:ss (YYYY =year, e.g. 1991, 2002, MM =month, e.g. June=06,
        DD = day of month (1-31), HH =hour, mm =minutes and ss =seconds).
        This is a character value, i.e. for 1200UTC 15 June 1991 the value set in
        <parameter>AXIS_DATE_MIN_VALUE</parameter> is '<code>1991-06-15 12:00:00</code>'.
        Likewise, the ending date should be set in <parameter>AXIS_DATE_MAX_VALUE</parameter>.
        The actual units used to plot the axis, i.e. days, months or years, is determined
        by the value set in <parameter>AXIS_DATE_TYPE</parameter>. The parameter
        <parameter>AXIS_TICK_INTERVAL</parameter> can be used to control the amount of
        major ticks to be plotted. For example if set to 2.0, every second tick will
        be plotted. <productname>Magics</productname> will calculate the appropriate
        date for each of the labels.</para>

        <para>The major ticks on the axis will represent the main units of the axis as
        given by <parameter>AXIS_DATE_TYPE</parameter>. Minor ticks may be plotted for
        the entity below the main units of the axis. For example, if <code>DAYS</code> are the
        main units, <code>HOURS</code> may be plotted as minor ticks. Minor ticks will not be
        labelled.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="Axis_Axis_Units">
        <title>Axis Units</title>

        <para>The units of the axis determine, to a large degree, the type of tick labels
        plotted. When set to '<code>HOURS</code>', it means that hours, days, months and
        years may appear on the axis tick labels. When set to '<code>DAYS</code>', it
        means that days, months and years may appear. If set to '<code>MONTHS</code>',
        only years and months may appear and, If <parameter>AXIS_DATE_UNITS</parameter>
        is set to '<code>YEARS</code>', only years may appear. Note that 'day'
        labels consist of the day of the week and the number of the day in the month.</para>
    </section>


    <section id="Axis_Tick_Labels">
        <title>Tick Labels</title>

        <para>The user may also decide to plot any combination of tick labels, i.e. year,
        month, day/date or hour. Parameters exist to enable this, i.e.
        <parameter>AXIS_HOURS_LABEL</parameter>, <parameter>AXIS_DAYS_LABEL</parameter>,
        <parameter>AXIS_MONTHS_LABEL</parameter> and <parameter>AXIS_YEARS_LABEL</parameter>.
        These parameters may be set to '<code>ON</code>' or '<code>OFF</code>'.
        The default is '<code>ON</code>', except for <parameter>AXIS_HOURS_LABEL</parameter>
        which is '<code>OFF</code>'.</para>


        <para>Furthermore, the parameter <parameter>AXIS_DAYS_LABEL</parameter> is
        different to the others as it may be set to '<code>DAY</code>', '<code>NUMBER</code>
        or '<code>BOTH</code>' as well as '<code>off</code>'. The default for
        <parameter>AXIS_DAYS_LABEL</parameter> is '<code>BOTH</code>'.</para>

        <para>Parameters exist to control the colour, height and quality of all the
        label types and, for <code>DAYS</code> and <code>MONTHS</code>, the number of
        characters in the name may be selected, e.g.
        <code>SEPTEMBER</code>, <code>SEP</code> or <code>S</code>. <!-- A full list of the
        date/time parameters is in appendix 1. --></para>
    </section>

    <section id="Axis_Axis_Grids">
        <title>Axis Grids</title>

        <para>For date/time axes only, axis grids may be positioned by the user, i.e.
        grids may be drawn in positions other than the tick positions. To achieve this,
        the parameter <parameter>AXIS_DATE_GRID_POSITIONING</parameter> should be set to 
        '<code>POSITIONAL</code>', the default being '<code>AUTOMATIC</code>'. A
        list of positions for placing the grids should be passed using the parameter
        <parameter>AXIS_DATE_GRID_POSITION</parameter> LIST, e.g.</para>

        <programlisting>    CALL <function>PSET1C</function> ('<parameter>AXIS_DATE_GRID_POSITION_LIST</parameter>',GLIS,N)</programlisting>

        <para>where <code>N</code> is the number of positions and <code>GLIS</code> is
        an array containing the positions which should be in the same format as
        <parameter>AXIS_DATE_MIN_VALUE</parameter> and <parameter>AXIS_DATE_MAX_VALUE</parameter>
        described above.</para>
     </section>


    <section id="Axis_Curve_Plotting">
        <title>Curve Plotting</title>

        <para>Please note that, when using a date/time axis, the X axis units used for
        plotting graphs (curves and bar charts) will have the format
        <code>YYYY-MM-DD HH:mm:ss</code> as described above.</para>
    </section>


  </section>  <!-- id="Axis_Date_Time" -->



  <xi:include href="../paramtables/paxis_tables.xml"
              xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

<!--
  <xi:include href="../paramtables/Axis_horizontal_axis_magml_tables.xml"
              xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
-->
  <xi:include href="../paramtables/Axis_horizontal_axis_magml_flat_tables.xml"
              xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
<!--
  <xi:include href="../paramtables/Axis_vertical_axis_magml_tables.xml"
              xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
-->
  <xi:include href="../paramtables/Axis_vertical_axis_magml_flat_tables.xml"
              xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

  <section id="Python_Axis_Examples">
      <title>Axis examples using Python</title>

      <para>The following example shows how to use a simple date axis in a Python program.</para>

      <programlisting>
<xi:include href="../examples/manual/python/source/axis_python.py_cc" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
      </programlisting>

      <figure id="figure_axis_py1Plot">
        <title>Resultant plot from example Python axis program</title>

        <mediaobject id="axis_pyPlot">
          <imageobject role="html">
            <imagedata fileref="images/python/axis_python_01.png" format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="fo">
            <imagedata fileref="../examples/manual/python/png/axis_python_01.png" format="PNG" depth="11cm"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The next example shows how to generate the same simple date axis with the MagMacro module in Python.</para>

      <programlisting>
<xi:include href="../examples/manual/python/source/axis_magmacro.py_cc" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
      </programlisting>

      <figure id="figure_axis_magmacro_py1Plot">
        <title>Resultant plot from example Python axis program</title>

        <mediaobject id="axis_magmacro_py1Plot">
          <imageobject role="html">
            <imagedata fileref="images/python/axis_magmacro_01.png" format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="fo">
            <imagedata fileref="../examples/manual/python/png/axis_magmacro_01.png" format="PNG" depth="11cm"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
  </section>


</chapter>
