<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                 "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd"> 

<chapter id="Data_Input" label="5">
  <title>Data Input</title>

  <xi:include href="../phrases/chapterinfo_mod.xml"
              xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

  <section id="Data_Introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>Data to be plotted can be presented to
    <productname>Magics</productname> in a number of ways, depending on its
    type: contour fields, wind fields, observations, symbols, axes, graphs and
    images.</para>

    <para>A contour field can be presented as either a rectangular array of
    grid point values or in GRIB code format. GRIB code itself can be
    presented as either an external file, or as a one dimensional data
    array.</para>

    <para>A wind field can be presented in GRIB code format or as a pair of
    rectangular arrays of grid point values<remark>, or as a single rectangular array
    of wind speed values (when plotting isotachs)</remark>. The pair of rectangular
    arrays can contain U and V velocity components<remark>, vorticity and divergence
    components</remark> or speed and direction components of the wind. GRIB code can be
    presented as either an external file, or as a pair of one dimensional data
    arrays. <remark>See Wind and Contour ARRAY Input</remark> and <remark>GRIB
    Code Input</remark> for full details on data input for contouring and wind
    plotting.</para>

    <para>Observation data must presented as an input file containing
    observations in WMO standard BUFR code.<remark> See OBSERVATION Data
    Input</remark>.</para>

    <para>Data for symbol plotting are presented in arrays, which should all
    have the same number of elements. Two arrays are used to pass the position
    information. There are four different types of symbol input data: markers,
    numbers, text and wind. NUMBER input data are passed as an real array,
    TEXT input data consists of text strings. MARKER input data consists of
    indices to <productname>Magics</productname> markers and wind input data consists of two arrays
    containing wind direction and speed respectively. Symbols can be plotted
    in INDIVIDUAL or TABLE mode. <remark>See SYMBOL Plotting Data
    Input</remark></para>

    <para>Typically, graph data are presented in two one-dimensional arrays,
    where one holds the X-axis values and the other holds the Y-axis values.
    <remark>See GRAPH Data Input</remark></para>

    <para>Satellite Image data must be presented in GRIB code<!--, as described in
    section <remark>IMAGE Data Input</remark>-->.</para>

    <para>Before presenting data to <productname>Magics</productname>, the
    users should firstly decide on the type of data and the method by which
    they wish to present it. The Diagrams with the
    <productname>Magics</productname> parameter charts in this chapter should
    help.</para>

    <para>When passing fields in GRIB code format, the necessary
    <productname>Magics</productname> INPUT parameters are automatically given
    appropriate values to ensure that a reasonable plot is obtained. When
    passing fields in array format, the user should select the appropriate
    values for the <productname>Magics</productname> INPUT parameters.</para>

    <para>Although the use of GRIB input is essentially easier than the use of
    array input, the description of GRIB input in this chapter occurs after
    that of array input. This is because the array input description explains
    the function of those parameters that are set automatically when using
    GRIB input.</para>

    <para>A contouring plot requires a single data field, whereas a wind plot
    requires two data fields for its full specification. The two fields can be
    U and V components or speed and direction components<remark> or vorticity and
    divergence components. Vorticity and divergence components can only be
    passed when using GRIB code data input. If isotachs are being plotted,
    then the field may be specified by the wind speed component only.</remark></para>
<important>
    <title>Magics++</title>
    Magics++ can not handle fields in spherical-harmonic representation. The user has to provide 
    the data on a Gaussian or regular grid. This has the advantage that expensive interpolations are not 
    performed when plotting data but at the time of retrieval. Most data users will handle are either in Gaussian or regular grid.
</important>
  <para></para>

  </section>

  <section id="Wind_and_Contour_ARRAY_Input">
    <title>Wind and Contour ARRAY Input</title>

    <para>Data fields are passed to <productname>Magics</productname> using
    the routine <function>PSET2R</function> as follows.</para>

    <para>Contouring Fields:</para>

    <programlisting>    CALL <function>PSET2R</function> ('<parameter>INPUT_FIELD</parameter>', C, M, N)</programlisting>

    <para>Wind Fields passed by U and V Components for plotting wind arrows
    and wind flags<remark>, streamlines and isotachs</remark>:</para>

    <programlisting>    CALL <function>PSET2R</function> ('<parameter>INPUT_WIND_U_COMPONENT</parameter>', W1, M, N)
    CALL <function>PSET2R</function> ('<parameter>INPUT_WIND_V_COMPONENT</parameter>', W2, M, N)</programlisting>

    <para>Wind Fields passed by Speed and Direction Components for plotting
    wind arrows and wind flags<remark>, streamlines and isotachs</remark>:</para>

    <programlisting>    CALL <function>PSET2R</function> ('<parameter>INPUT_WIND_SPEED</parameter>', W1, M, N)
    CALL <function>PSET2R</function> ('<parameter>INPUT_WIND_DIRECTION</parameter>', W2, M, N)</programlisting>

<remark>
    <para>Wind Fields passed by Speed Component for plotting isotachs:</para>

    <programlisting>    CALL <function>PSET2R</function> ('<parameter>INPUT_WIND_SPEED</parameter>', W1, M, N)</programlisting>
</remark>

    <para>where <code>C</code> is an array <code>C(M,N)</code> containing a
    contouring field, <code>W1</code> and <code>W2</code> are arrays
    <code>W1(M,N)</code>, <code>W2(M,N)</code> containing the components of a
    wind field, <code>M</code> is the number of points in the direction of the
    first index and <code>N</code> is the number of points in the direction of
    the second index.</para>

    <para>See <olink targetdoc="Magics_data" targetptr="table_InputMatrix_parameters" />
    for a list of all the available parameters for accessing data stored in
    arrays.</para>

  </section>

  <section id="Organization_of_the_Input_Field">
    <title>Organization of the Input Field</title>

    <para>If the field is passed in array form, the user needs to describe how
    the array is to be mapped onto the subplot or geographical area which the
    array covers.</para>

    <para>The input field organization is controlled by the parameter
    <parameter>INPUT_FIELD_ORGANIZATION</parameter> which can have two values:
    '<code>REGULAR</code>' or '<code>GAUSSIAN</code>',
    the default value being '<code>REGULAR</code>'.</para>

    <para>For a regular field, the default values for the parameters
    concerning array organization are set for a global latitude/ longitude
    field with 1.5 degrees resolution in both directions, going from 90.0
    degrees north to 90.0 degrees south in latitude and from 0.0 degrees to
    358.5 degrees in longitude.</para>

    <para>For a gaussian field, the default values for the parameters
    concerning array organization are set for a global latitude/ longitude
    field with 1.125 degrees resolution in longitude and 1.1213 degrees in
    latitude, going from 89.142 degrees north to 89.142 degrees south in
    latitude and from 0.0 degrees to 358.875 degrees in longitude. (This
    conforms to a ECMWF T106 model post processed surface field).</para>


    <important> <title>Magics++</title>
    With <productname>Magics++</productname>, the concept of a 'FITTED' matrix no longer
    exists. The correct approach is to plot in a CARTESIAN projection and set
    <parameter>INPUT_FIELD_INITIAL_X</parameter>, <parameter>INPUT_FIELD_FINAL_X</parameter>,
    <parameter>INPUT_FIELD_INITIAL_Y</parameter> and <parameter>INPUT_FIELD_FINAL_Y</parameter>. 
    </important>

  </section>




  <section id="REGULAR_Spaced_Latitude_Longitude_Grid">
    <title>REGULAR Spaced Latitude/Longitude Grid</title>

    <para>When <parameter>INPUT_FIELD_ORGANIZATION</parameter> is set to
    '<code>REGULAR</code>' the field is assumed to be on a regular
    latitude/longitude grid.</para>

    <para><productname>Magics</productname> will perform the contouring in
    this grid and then plot the result according to the subpage mapping
    parameters, i.e. the field can either be global or a subpart of the field.
    Since the contouring is performed in the original grid it is ensured that
    all field values are taken into account when the isolines are generated.
    When using this method, a full specification of the input array is
    required:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The longitude and latitude position of the first element, (1,1),
        in the array may be set with the parameters:</para>

        <programlisting>    <parameter>INPUT_FIELD_INITIAL_LONGITUDE</parameter>
    <parameter>INPUT_FIELD_INITIAL_LATITUDE</parameter></programlisting>

        <para>The default values are <code>0.0</code> and <code>90.0</code>,
        respectively.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The step lengths between positions of array elements in
        longitude and latitude directions are set by using the
        parameters:</para>

        <programlisting>    <parameter>INPUT_FIELD_LONGITUDE_STEP</parameter>
    <parameter>INPUT_FIELD_LATITUDE_STEP</parameter></programlisting>

        <para>Positive values indicate for longitudes that the positions go
        from west to east and for latitudes from south to north. Negative
        values are used to indicate opposite directions.</para>

        <para>The default values are <code>1.5</code> for
        <parameter>INPUT_FIELD_LONGITUDE_STEP</parameter> and
        <code>-1.5</code> for
        <parameter>INPUT_FIELD_LATITUDE_STEP</parameter>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>By default the first index of the array refers to longitude
        positions and the second index refers to latitudes. If these are
        interchanged, <parameter>INPUT_FIELD_PRIMARY_INDEX</parameter> should
        be set to '<code>LATITUDE</code>'. Default is
        '<code>LONGITUDE</code>'.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The following is a full list of the default values for
        describing the default input field with a regular grid.</para>

        <programlisting>    <parameter>INPUT_FIELD_INITIAL_LATITUDE</parameter>      90.0
    <parameter>INPUT_FIELD_INITIAL_LONGITUDE</parameter>      0.0
    <parameter>INPUT_FIELD_LONGITUDE_STEP</parameter>         1.5
    <parameter>INPUT_FIELD_LATITUDE_STEP</parameter>         -1.5
    <parameter>INPUT_FIELD_PRIMARY_INDEX</parameter>          LONGITUDE</programlisting>

        <para>In the default situation, the contouring or wind field array(s)
        passed to <productname>Magics</productname> via
        <function>PSET2R</function> should have dimensions of 240 in the
        direction of the first index and 121 in the direction of the second
        index.</para>

      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="GAUSSIAN_Grid">
    <title>GAUSSIAN Grid</title>

    <para>When <parameter>INPUT_FIELD_ORGANIZATION</parameter> is set to
    '<code>GAUSSIAN</code>', <productname>Magics</productname> will accept
    fields on a gaussian grid, even though the field is not regularly
    spaced.</para>

    <para>The distance between grid points for gaussian grid fields is regular
    in the longitude direction but irregular in the latitude direction.
    However the variance in the grid distance along the irregularly spaced
    line is small enough that it may be regarded as regular and
    <productname>Magics</productname> makes this assumption.</para>

    <para>Users should set <parameter>INPUT_FIELD_LATITUDE_STEP</parameter> to
    the average value of the latitude grid interval, which should be
    calculated as accurately as possible.</para>

    <para>The following is a full list of the default values for the
    parameters describing an input field with a gaussian grid. (i.e. an ECMWF
    T106 model post processed surface field).</para>

    <programlisting><parameter>    INPUT_FIELD_INITIAL_LATITUDE</parameter>         89.142
    <parameter>INPUT_FIELD_INITIAL_LONGITUDE</parameter>         0.0
    <parameter>INPUT_FIELD_LONGITUDE_STEP</parameter>            1.125
    <parameter>INPUT_FIELD_LATITUDE_STEP</parameter>             1.1213
    <parameter>INPUT_FIELD_PRIMARY_INDEX</parameter>             LONGITUDE</programlisting>

    <para>In the default situation, the contouring or wind field array(s)
    passed to <productname>Magics</productname> via
    <function>PSET2R</function> should have dimensions of 320 in the direction
    of the first index and 160 in the direction of the second index.</para>
  </section>


  <section id="Data_Suppression">
    <title>Data Suppression</title>

    <para>By using the suppress parameters
    <parameter>INPUT_FIELD_SUPPRESS_ABOVE</parameter> and
    <parameter>INPUT_FIELD_SUPPRESS_BELOW</parameter>, users may suppress data
    values beyond a certain value in a contouring or wind field. This may be
    necessary when the user is aware that some of his data are invalid above
    or below a certain value.</para>

    <para>In the case of a contouring field, suppression means that the data
    values outside the permitted range are eliminated before any calculation
    of contour levels or gradient estimation takes place.</para>

    <para>For example, by setting
    <parameter>INPUT_FIELD_SUPPRESS_ABOVE</parameter> to <code>1.0E20</code> ,
    all contour levels above <code>1.0E20</code> would be suppressed. Please
    note that the suppress parameters should only be used to suppress invalid
    data. If used wrongly, the data plotted may not be accurate, particularly
    contour maxima/minima values.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="GRIB_Code_Input">
    <title>GRIB Code Input</title>

    <para>To facilitate the plotting of GRIB code fields, there is an
    interface that enables users to plot GRIB code with a minimum of
    programming effort. The action routine is called <function>PGRIB</function>.</para>

    <para><productname>Magics</productname> uses ECMWF's GRIB_API for the decoding
    of GRIB files. See
    <ulink url="http://www.ecmwf.int/products/data/software/grib_api.html">GRIB_API</ulink>
    for more details.</para>

    <para>Note that the GRIB_API supports the updating of definition files without the
    need for a new release of the library. This is enabled through setting the environment
    variable</para>

    <para><code>GRIB_DEFINITION_PATH</code></para>

    <para>to the path where the new definition files reside.</para>



    <para>See <olink targetdoc="Magics_data" targetptr="pgrib_tables" />
    for a list of all the available parameters for accessing GRIB data.</para>
</section>

    <section id="Pseudo_Action_Routine_PGRIB">
      <title>Pseudo Action Routine PGRIB</title>

      <para>The pseudo action routine <function>PGRIB</function> allows the
      automatic processing of GRIB code data. Users may call
      <function>PGRIB</function> to decode GRIB code data and, if required, to
      set the appropriate <productname>Magics</productname> input field,
      contour, wind, image and text parameters. <function>PGRIB</function> can
      deal with GRIB code on regular and Gaussian grids.<remark> It can also deal with
      GRIB coded polar stereographic data and with stretched/rotated GRIB
      data.</remark></para>

      <para>Basically, <function>PGRIB</function> will set up
      <productname>Magics</productname> parameters for plotting one
      meteorological field each time it is called. This field could be a wind
      field, which requires two input GRIB fields, normally U and
      V. The user will maintain the responsibility for setting up the
      page layout and mapping parameters as well as calling the action
      routines to perform the plotting, i.e. <function>PCONT</function>,
      <function>PWIND</function>, <function>PIMAGE</function> and
      <function>PTEXT</function>.</para>

      <para>There are some <productname>Magics</productname> parameters
      associated with <function>PGRIB</function> that should be set before
      <function>PGRIB</function> is called. These parameters are explained
      later as are all the functions of <function>PGRIB</function>.</para>

      <para>The format for calling pseudo action routine
      <function>PGRIB</function> is <code>CALL PGRIB</code>, with no
      arguments. It is necessary to call <function>PGRIB</function> before any
      action routine that requires the decoded data. After calling
      <function>PGRIB</function> and before calling an action routine, the
      user may set or reset any of the contouring, text, image or wind
      parameters, if required.<!-- The user may supply two arrays into which
      <function>PGRIB</function> can pass back information about the type of
      field, level etc. <function>PGRIB</function> will also set a <productname>Magics</productname>
      parameter to inform the user which action routine should be called, or
      if an error has occurred while handling the GRIB code field. This
      mechanism enables users to decide which actions to take after calling
      <function>PGRIB</function>.--></para>

      <para>GRIB code may be passed to <productname>Magics</productname> as an
      input file or in a one dimensional array.</para>

    </section>

    <section id="Functions_of_PGRIB">
      <title>Functions of PGRIB</title>

      <para>Depending on the user's requirements, <function>PGRIB</function>
      can perform some or all of the following functions:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Decode GRIB data.</para>
        </listitem>

<!--
        <listitem>
          <para>Convert upper air fields from spectral to grid point, if
          necessary. The user may supply the resolution of the grid point
          field by setting a <productname>Magics</productname>
          parameter.</para>
        </listitem>
-->

        <listitem>
          <para>Scale the meteorological fields, i.e. convert fields to
          standard units for plotting purposes, e.g. convert temperature
          fields from Kelvin to Celsius. The user may request, by setting a
          <productname>Magics</productname> parameter, that the fields should
          not be scaled. The standard units used by <function>PGRIB</function>
          can be found in the section on GRIB Table 2.</para>
        </listitem>

<!--
a) is this true?
b) does the user need to know it?
        <listitem>
          <para>Set <parameter>INPUT_FIELD</parameter> parameters to the
          appropriate values. These parameters include
          <parameter>INPUT_FIELD_ORGANIZATION</parameter>.
          <function>PGRIB</function> will handle the setting up of the array
          for contouring etc by calling <function>PSET2R</function>. This
          feature relieves the user of the responsibility for setting the
          <parameter>INPUT_FIELD</parameter> parameters.</para>
        </listitem>
-->
        <listitem>
          <para>Build <productname>Magics</productname> text blocks to
          describe the data field. This text will include such information as
          time/date and type of field. Users may reset
          <productname>Magics</productname> text parameters after calling
          <function>PGRIB</function> and before calling action
          routines.</para>
        </listitem>

<!--
This does not seem to be true (as of 06/02/2007)
        <listitem>
          <para>Set appropriate <productname>Magics</productname> contouring,
          wind and image parameters. This is achieved in
          <productname>Magics</productname> by retrieving the appropriate
          specification group from a library of such groups. This library
          contains a separate specification group for each type of
          meteorological field that is likely to be required. An example of a
          specification group from the library is given later. Users may reset
          any contouring or wind parameters by calling the appropriate
          parameter setting routines after calling <function>PGRIB</function>.
          <function>PGRIB</function> also sets up the appropriate
          <productname>Magics</productname> parameters for plotting satellite
          image data.</para>
        </listitem>
-->
        <listitem>
          <para>If the map required is not a global map,
          <function>PGRIB</function> can extract a subarea from the input
          field so that it covers almost exactly the geographic area required
          to be plotted. This helps reduce memory when contouring.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

<!--
    <section id="Modes_of_PGRIB">
      <title>Modes of PGRIB</title>

      <para></para>

      <highlights>
        <para>Check all of this page for accuracy with regards to
        Magics++</para>
      </highlights>
    </section>
-->



    <section id="Observation_Data_Input">
      <title>Observation Data Input</title>

This section needs to be thoroughly reviewed!

      <para>Data for observation plotting may be presented to
      <productname>Magics</productname> in the form of an input BUFR file<remark> or in an
      array</remark>.</para>

      <para>The parameter <parameter>OBS_INPUT_TYPE</parameter> may be set to
      inform <productname>Magics</productname> of the data input type. It
      should be set to '<code>ARRAY</code>' if the input data is in an array.
      The default value is '<code>FILE</code>'.</para>

      <para>An array may be used if only one observation is to be plotted, in
      which case the parameter <parameter>OBS_INPUT_FIELD</parameter> should
      be set using <function>PSET2R</function>.</para>

      <programlisting>CALL PSET1C ('OBS_INPUT_TYPE', 'ARRAY')
CALL PSET1I ('OBS_INPUT_FIELD', IFIELD, N)</programlisting>

      <para>where <code>IFIELD</code> is an integer array of dimension
      <code>N.</code></para>

      <para><code>For passing more than one observation, an input file should
      be used, which can contain any number of observations of varying
      observation types and code types.</code></para>

      <para><code>In this case, the parameter
      <parameter>OBS_INPUT_FILE_UNIT</parameter> should be set using
      <function>PSETI</function>, for example:</code> <programlisting>CALL PSETI ('OBS_INPUT_FILE_UNIT', 2)</programlisting></para>

      <para>informs <productname>Magics</productname> that data for
      observation plotting is on file unit 2.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="Data_BUFR_Tables">
      <title>BUFR Tables</title>

      <para>To enable the decoding of observations coded in BUFR, it is
      necessary to have tables which describe the contents of the BUFR code,
      e.g. the names and units of parameters, reference values and scale
      factors. The "parameters", as understood in the BUFR context, include
      not just the meteorological variables, but also the location of the
      observation, block/station number, instrumentation etc. Each parameter
      is described by a descriptor, which is an integer number that uniquely
      identifies the parameter, e.g. Temperature, Pressure,
      latitude/longitude, block number. These BUFR tables are stored at an
      address defined by an environment variable (which is made known to
      <productname>Magics</productname> installers at the various sites). The
      tables are then used in the BUFR decoding part of
      <productname>Magics</productname> and their use is transparent to the
      user. There are standard descriptor numbers for each of the
      "parameters". It is possible to use local descriptor numbers instead of
      the standard ones and these local descriptors would be described in the
      BUFR tables.</para>

      <para>The EMOSLIB library is used for the handling of BUFR data. It is possible
      to specify a path to a different set of tables by setting the the environment variable</para>
      <para><code>BUFR_TABLES</code></para>
      <para>to the path where the tables reside. An example value for this variable would be:
      <filename>/home/ma/emos/tables/bufr/linux/000240</filename>.</para>

    </section>

    <section id="Data_BUFR_Parameter_Lists">
      <title>BUFR Parameter Lists</title>

      <para>To make it possible for <productname>Magics</productname> to be
      able to plot observations from BUFR code from varying originating
      centres, which may or may not use local descriptor numbers, it is
      necessary for <productname>Magics</productname> to be able to identify
      the descriptor numbers of the meteorological variables and those
      "parameters" that describe the position and time of the observation. To
      enable this for each originating centre, there are external files called
      BUFR Parameter Lists, where each file consists of a list of descriptors
      for the meteorological variables and the position and time "parameters".
      For each originating centre, these descriptor numbers should match those
      in the BUFR Tables described above.</para>

      <para>There are two BUFR Parameter Lists for each originating centre,
      one for surface observations and one for upper air. Each list consists
      of entry lines, one entry line per meteorological variable or
      "parameter". An entry line consists of a descriptor number followed by
      an ampersand(&amp;) and then, optionally, text to describe the
      variable.</para>

      <para><token>descriptor &amp; text describing the meteorological
      variable</token></para>

      <para>For example, the first three lines of the upper air BUFR Parameter
      List should be as follows:</para>

      <programlisting>11001 &amp; WIND DIRECTION
11002 &amp; WIND SPEED
10195 &amp; HEIGHT in mtrs</programlisting>

      <para>The position of the line in the list, not the text, is what
      actually defines the meteorological variable, e.g. the first entry line
      in the upper air BUFR Parameter Table is always the entry for Wind
      Direction, the second Wind Speed and the third Height. It is necessary
      to include each entry line in the file, even if they are not to be used.
      Complete lists for upper air and surface are given below.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="Data_Accessing_BUFR_Parameter_Lists">
      <title>Accessing BUFR Parameter Lists</title>

      <para>There are two modes of accessing the BUFR Parameter Lists in
      <productname>Magics</productname>. By default, the lists are stored at
      an address path controlled by an environment variable, which is made
      known to installers at the various sites. The other mode of access is by
      setting a <productname>Magics</productname> parameter,
      <parameter>BUFR_PARAM_TABLE_ADDRESS_PATH</parameter>, to the address
      path of the tables. This means that users can then force
      <productname>Magics</productname> to use their own lists. Each upper air
      list name should have the format <token>bufrtab_ua_nn</token> (surface
      lists should have the format <token>bufrtab_surf_nn</token> ) where
      <token>nn</token> is the number of the originating Centre of the BUFR
      data, e.g. 98 for ECMWF, 85 for France.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="Data_Surface_BUFR_Parameter_List">
      <title>Surface BUFR Parameter List</title>

      <para>The ECMWF BUFR Parameter List for surface data,
      <token>bufrtab_surf_98</token> is as follows (38 lines):</para>

      <programlisting>11011 &amp; WIND DIRECTION at 10 m
11012 &amp; WIND SPEED at 10m
20001 &amp; HORIZONTAL VISIBILITY
20003 &amp; PRESENT WEATHER
12004 &amp; TEMPERATURE at 2m
20012 &amp; MEDIUM CLOUD
20012 &amp; HIGH CLOUD
10051 &amp; MSL PRESSURE
10063 &amp; PRESSURE TENDENCY CHARACTERISTIC (a)
10061 &amp; PRESSURE TENDENCY AMOUNT (pp)
20004 &amp; PAST WEATHER (1)
20005 &amp; PAST WEATHER (2)
20011 &amp; CLOUD AMOUNT (nh)
20013 &amp; HEIGHT OF CLOUD BASE (h)
20012 &amp; LOW CLOUD
12006 &amp; DEWPOINT at 2m
22042 &amp; SEA TEMPERATURE
1012  &amp; SHIP'S DIRECTION
1013  &amp; SHIP'S SPEED
20010 &amp; TOTAL CLOUD
22002 &amp; DIRECTION OF WIND WAVES
22012 &amp; PERIOD OF WIND WAVES
22022 &amp; HEIGHT OF WIND WAVES
22003 &amp; DIRECTION OF SWELL WAVES
22013 &amp; PERIOD OF SWELL WAVES
22023 &amp; HEIGHT OF SWELL WAVES
22001 &amp; DIRECTION OF WAVES
22011 &amp; PERIOD OF WAVES
20021 &amp; HEIGHT OF WAVES
4004  &amp; HOUR
4005  &amp; MINUTE
5001  &amp; LATITUDE (HIGH ACCURACY)
5002  &amp; LATITUDE (COARSE ACCURACY)
6001  &amp; LONGITUDE (HGIH ACCURACY)
6002  &amp; LONGITUDE (COARSE ACCURACY)
7001  &amp; HEIGHT OF STATION in mtrs
7061  &amp; DEPTH BELOW LAND SURFACE
12030 &amp; SOIL TEMPERATURES</programlisting>

      <para>To make local surface BUFR Parameter Lists, it is only necessary
      to copy the above ECMWF surface list to a new list (with an appropriate
      name) and change the descriptor numbers to the ones to be used locally.
      It is important that all the above lines are included in each list, even
      if they are not to be used in plotting.</para>

      <para>The position and time "parameters" are only given in the surface
      list.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="Data_Upper_Air_BUFR_Parameter_List">
      <title>Upper Air BUFR Parameter List</title>

      <para>Following is a listing of all the entries in the ECMWF BUFR
      Parameter List for upper air, <code>bufrtab_ua_98</code> (18
      lines):</para>

      <programlisting>11001 &amp; WIND DIRECTION
11002 &amp; WIND SPEED
10195 &amp; HEIGHT in mtrs
12003 &amp; DEW POINT TEMPERATURE
12001 &amp; TEMPERATURE
7004  &amp; PRESSURE level in pascals
7006  &amp; HEIGHT ABOVE STATION in mtrs
22042 &amp; SEA TEMPERATURE
11003 &amp; U-COMPONENT
11004 &amp; V-COMPONENT
10003 &amp; HEIGHT in gp mtrs
11192 &amp; U-COMPONENT at 10m
11193 &amp; V-COMPONENT at 10m
7002  &amp; ALTITUDE in mtrs
12007 &amp; VIRTUAL TEMPERATURE
13016 &amp; PRECIPITABLE WATER
20010 &amp; TOTAL CLOUD
10004 &amp; PRESSURE in pascals</programlisting>

      <para>To make local upper air BUFR Parameter Lists, it is only necessary
      to copy the above ECMWF upper air list to a new list (with an
      appropriate name) and change the descriptor numbers to the ones to be
      used locally. It is important that all the above lines are included in
      each list, even if they are not to be used in plotting.</para>

      <highlights>
        <para>Diagram 8</para>
      </highlights>
    </section>
 


  <section id="SYMBOL_Plotting_Data_Input">
    <title>Symbol Plotting Data Input</title>

    <para>There are three different types of SYMBOL input data, i.e. numbers,
    text and markers. The parameter <parameter>SYMBOL_TYPE</parameter> is used
    to define the type of symbol required, e.g.</para>

    <programlisting>    CALL <function>PSETC</function> ('<parameter>SYMBOL_TYPE</parameter>','MARKER')</programlisting>

    <para>It can have one of four values, <code>NUMBER</code> (default),
    <code>TEXT</code>, <code>MARKER</code> or <code>WIND</code>. Only one of
    the above four types can be plotted in any one call to
    <function>PSYMB</function>.</para>

    <para><code>NUMBER</code> input data are the actual numbers to be plotted
    and are passed as follows:</para>

    <programlisting>    CALL <function>PSET1R</function> ('<parameter>SYMBOL_INPUT_NUMBER_LIST</parameter>',RARAY,N)</programlisting>

    <para>where <code>RARAY</code> is a real array of <code>N</code>
    elements.</para>

    <para><code>TEXT</code> input data consists of text strings which are to
    be plotted and are passed as follows:</para>

    <programlisting>    CALL <function>PSET1C</function> ('<parameter>SYMBOL_INPUT_TEXT_LIST</parameter>',CARAY,N)</programlisting>

    <para>where <code>CARAY</code> is a character array of <code>N</code>
    elements.</para>

    <para><code>MARKER</code> input data consists of indices to
    <productname>Magics</productname> markers<remark>(see Figure XII-2 on page
    XII-13)</remark> and are passed as follows:</para>

    <programlisting>    CALL <function>PSET1I</function> ('<parameter>SYMBOL_INPUT_MARKER_LIST</parameter>',IARAY,N)</programlisting>

    <para>where <code>IARAY</code> is an integer array of <code>N</code>
    elements.</para>

    <para><code>WIND</code> data consists of the wind speed and direction and
    are passed as follows:</para>

    <programlisting>    CALL <function>PSETR</function> ('<parameter>SYMBOL_INPUT_WIND_SPEED</parameter>', SPARAY,N)
    CALL <function>PSETR</function> ('<parameter>SYMBOL_INPUT_WIND_DIRECTION</parameter>',DARAY,N)</programlisting>

    <para>where <code>SPARAY</code> and <code>DARAY</code> are real arrays of
    <code>N</code> elements.</para>

    <para>The <code>POSITION</code> arrays and the <code>DATA INPUT</code>
    arrays should all have the same number of elements. The symbol in the i-th
    element of the <code>DATA</code> array will be plotted in the position
    given by the i-th elements of the <code>POSITION</code> arrays. It is the
    user's responsibility to ensure that they correspond correctly. If the
    arrays are of different lengths, <productname>Magics</productname> will
    limit all the arrays to the size of the smallest array and a warning
    message will be printed.</para>

    <para><code>TABLE</code> mode allows users to plot symbols within
    specified ranges of values and with varying colours and heights. To plot
    symbols in <code>TABLE</code> mode the parameter
    <parameter>SYMBOL_TABLE_MODE</parameter> should be set to
    '<code>ON</code>' . When calling <function>PSYMB</function> in
    <code>TABLE</code> mode, the user must pass information to
    <productname>Magics</productname> to describe the minimum and maximum of
    each range required and may also pass information to describe the height
    and/or colour for each of the desired ranges. All this information should
    be passed in the form of tables and <productname>Magics</productname>
    parameters exist to enable this. <remark>Example PROGRAM DATA05 gives a
    description of plotting NUMBER symbols in TABLE mode.</remark> The
    parameters for passing the minimum and maximum of the ranges are
    <parameter>SYMBOL_MIN_TABLE</parameter> and
    <parameter>SYMBOL_MAX_TABLE</parameter> , respectively. The minimum values
    of the required ranges may be passed to <productname>Magics</productname>
    as follows:</para>

    <programlisting>    CALL <function>PSET1R</function> ('<parameter>SYMBOL_MIN_TABLE</parameter>',RMIN,N)</programlisting>

    <para>where <code>RMIN</code> is a real array of <code>N</code> elements.
    The maximum values should be placed in the corresponding elements of an
    array and passed to <productname>Magics</productname> as follows:</para>

    <programlisting>    CALL <function>PSET1R</function> ('<parameter>SYMBOL_MAX_TABLE</parameter>',RMAX,N)</programlisting>

    <para>where <code>RMAX</code> is a real array of <code>N</code> elements.
    The colour to be used for each of the ranges may be passed using the
    parameter <parameter>SYMBOL_COLOUR_TABLE</parameter>, e.g.</para>

    <programlisting>    CALL <function>PSET1C</function> ('<parameter>SYMBOL_COLOUR_TABLE</parameter>',COLTAB,N)</programlisting>

    <para>where <code>COLTAB</code> is a character array of <code>N</code>
    elements. Similarly, the heights for each range may be passed as
    follows:</para>

    <programlisting>    CALL <function>PSET1R</function> ('<parameter>SYMBOL_HEIGHT_TABLE</parameter>',HGTAB,N)</programlisting>

    <para>The following will enable the passing of text for each of the ranges
    in table mode:</para>

    <programlisting>    CALL <function>PSET1C</function> ('<parameter>SYMBOL_TEXT_TABLE</parameter>',TEXTAB,N)</programlisting>

    <para>Passing marker data for each of the ranges in table mode is achieved
    as follows:</para>

    <programlisting>    CALL <function>PSET1I</function> ('<parameter>SYMBOL_MARKER_TABLE</parameter>',SYMTAB,N)</programlisting>

  </section>

 
  <section id="ODB_Input">
    <title>ODB Data Input</title>

    <para>With <productname>Magics++</productname>, <productname>Magics</productname> has the facility
    to import data from an ODB database using the action routine
    <function>PODB</function> and its associated parameters. A portion of
    FORTRAN code will show the basic usage and a discussion will
    follow.</para>

    <programlisting>
      CALL <function>PSETC</function>('<parameter>odb_database</parameter>',
     +             'odb://server/dir/subdir/database_file')

      CALL <function>PSETC</function> ('<parameter>odb_query</parameter>',
     +              'SELECT lat, lon, obsvalue 
     +               FROM   hdr, body 
     +               WHERE  varno=$t2m AND obsvalue IS NOT null')
      
      CALL <function>PSETC</function> ('<parameter>odb_latitude</parameter>',    'lat@hdr')
      CALL <function>PSETC</function> ('<parameter>odb_longitude</parameter>',   'lon@hdr')
      CALL <function>PSETC</function> ('<parameter>odb_observation</parameter>', 'obsvalue@body')
      CALL <function>PSETI</function> ('<parameter>odb_nb_rows</parameter>',      200000)
      CALL <function>PODB</function>
    </programlisting>

    <para>The first thing is to set the path to the database using the
    parameter <parameter>ODB_DATABASE</parameter>. An SQL query to retrieve
    the data is set in the parameter <parameter>ODB_QUERY</parameter>.
    Parameters <parameter>ODB_LATITUDE</parameter>,
    <parameter>ODB_LONGITUDE</parameter> and
    <parameter>ODB_OBSERVATION</parameter> are used to identify the columns
    containing the latitude, longitude and observation values in the data;
    also available is the parameter <parameter>ODB_LEVEL</parameter>.</para>

    <para>For curve plotting, the parameters <parameter>ODB_X</parameter> and
    <parameter>ODB_Y</parameter> can be set to the names of the columns to be
    used for the x- and y-coordinates.</para>

    <para><remark>ODB_PARAMETERS</remark></para>

    <para>The start row and the maximum number of rows to retrieve can be set
    using the parameters <parameter>ODB_STARTING_ROW</parameter> and
    <parameter>ODB_NB_ROWS</parameter> respectively.</para>

    <para>Finally, the action routine <function>PODB</function> is called
    without any parameters. The resulting data may be plotting using the
    symbol plotting routines
    <!--(see <olink targetdoc="Magics_symbol" targetptr="Symbol_Plotting" />) -->
    or the curve plotting routines<remark>(see ???)</remark>.</para>

    <para>Note that the automatic title that <productname>Magics++</productname> produces
    for data retrieved from the ODB data is the query itself.</para>
    
    <!--<para>See <olink targetdoc="Magics_data" targetptr="table_OdbDecoder_parameters" />
    for a list of all the available parameters for accessing ODB data.</para>-->

  </section>

  <section id="NetCDF_Data_Input">
    <title>NetCDF Data Input</title>

    <para><productname>Magics++</productname> is capable of
    reading NetCDF data files. A
    portion of FORTRAN code will show the basic usage and a discussion will
    follow.</para>

    <programlisting>
    CALL <function>PSETC</function> ('<parameter>NETCDF_FILENAME</parameter>',                'data/rh850.nc')
    CALL <function>PSETC</function> ('<parameter>NETCDF_FIELD_VARIABLE_NAME</parameter>',     'r')
    CALL <function>PSETC</function> ('<parameter>NETCDF_LATITUDE_VARIABLE_NAME</parameter>',  'latitude')
    CALL <function>PSETC</function> ('<parameter>NETCDF_LONGITUDE_VARIABLE_NAME</parameter>', 'longitude')
    CALL <function>PSETR</function> ('<parameter>NETCDF_FIELD_SCALING_FACTOR</parameter>',     1.0)
    CALL <function>PSETR</function> ('<parameter>NETCDF_FIELD_ADD_OFFSET</parameter>',         0.0)
    CALL <function>PNETCDF</function>
    </programlisting>

    <para>The path to the file to be read is set via
    <parameter>NETCDF_FILENAME</parameter>. The variables in the NetCDF file
    to be used as latitude, longitude and value are specified using the
    parameters <parameter>NETCDF_LATITUDE_VARIABLE_NAME</parameter>,
    <parameter>NETCDF_LONGITUDE_VARIABLE_NAME</parameter>, and
    <parameter>NETCDF_FIELD_VARIABLE_NAME</parameter> respectively. The
    resultant data values can be multiplied by setting
    <parameter>NETCDF_FIELD_SCALING_FACTOR</parameter> to a value other than
    <code>1.0</code>, and a constant added to each value via the parameter
    <parameter>NETCDF_FIELD_ADD_OFFSET</parameter>.</para>

    <para><remark>Parameters netcdf_dimension_setting, netcdf_x_variable_name,
    netcdf_y_variable_name, netcdf_y_transformation, netcdf_type,
    netcdf_convention.</remark></para>

    <para>Finally, the action routine <function>PNETCDF</function> is called
    without any parameters. Note that in the above example, most of the
    parameters are not required as their default values are the same. See
    <olink targetdoc="Magics_data" targetptr="pnetcdf_tables" />
    for the complete list of parameters and their defaults.<!-- See
    <olink targetdoc="Magics_data" targetptr="Program_data_netcdf" /> for
    a complete program which further illustrates the use of NetCDF data
    in <productname>Magics</productname>.--></para>

    <para>Note that <productname>Magics</productname> does not currently produce
    an automatic title for NetCDF data - an appropriate title should be
    supplied by the user.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="GRAPH_Data_Input">
    <title>GRAPH Data Input</title>

    <para>All input data for graph plotting are passed to
    <productname>Magics</productname> via arrays. The parameter
    <parameter>GRAPH_TYPE</parameter> is used to describe the type of graph
    required. Valid values are <code>CURVE</code> (default), <code>BAR</code>
    and <code>AREA</code>.</para>

    <para>When set to <code>CURVE</code>, two one-dimensional arrays are used
    to pass the data describing the curve, e.g.</para>

    <programlisting>    CALL <function>PSET1R</function> ('<parameter>GRAPH_CURVE_X_VALUES</parameter>',XAR,M)
    CALL <function>PSET1R</function> ('<parameter>GRAPH_CURVE_Y_VALUES</parameter>',YAR,M)</programlisting>

    <para>where <code>XAR</code> and <code>YAR</code> are arrays of
    <code>M</code> elements. The first array should contain the X values and
    the second array should contain the Y values.</para>

    <para>If <parameter>GRAPH_TYPE</parameter> is set to '<code>AREA</code>' ,
    users may shade the area between two curves. The first curve is defined in
    the same way as for '<code>CURVE</code>' and the second one as
    follows:</para>

    <programlisting>    CALL <function>PSET1R</function> ('<parameter>GRAPH_CURVE2_X_VALUES</parameter>',XAR2,M2)
    CALL <function>PSET1R</function> ('<parameter>GRAPH_CURVE2_Y_VALUES</parameter>',YAR2,M2)</programlisting>

    <para>Input data for <code>BAR</code> charts are passed in three arrays as
    follows:</para>

    <programlisting>    CALL <function>PSET1R</function> ('<parameter>GRAPH_BAR_X_VALUES</parameter>',XAR1,M)
    CALL <function>PSET1R</function> ('<parameter>GRAPH_BAR_Y_LOWER_VALUES</parameter>',YAR1,M)
    CALL <function>PSET1R</function> ('<parameter>GRAPH_BAR_Y_UPPER_VALUES</parameter>',YAR2,M)</programlisting>

    <para>where <code>XAR1</code>, <code>YAR1</code> and <code>YAR2</code> are
    arrays of <code>M</code> elements each. <code>XAR1</code> should contain
    the X values for the bars. The lengths of the bars in the Y direction are
    defined by their upper and lower Y values. This means that users have the
    capability of plotting 'hidden' and 'overlapping' <code>BAR</code>
    charts.</para>
  </section>


  <xi:include href="../paramtables/pgrib_tables.xml"
              xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

  <!--
  <xi:include href="../paramtables/pbufr_tables.xml"
              xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
-->

  <xi:include href="../paramtables/pnetcdf_tables.xml"
              xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

  <!--
 <xi:include href="../paramtables/psymb_tables.xml"
              xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
 -->

<!--
 <xi:include href="../paramtables/podb_tables.xml"
              xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
-->


 <xi:include href="../paramtables/input_matrix_tables.xml"
              xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />



 <section id = 'GRIB_input_magml_all_tables'>
   <title>MagML Templates for GRIB Input</title>

   <xi:include href="../paramtables/GribDecoder_grib_magml_tables.xml"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

   <xi:include href="../paramtables/GribDecoder_grib_magml_flat_tables.xml"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
</section>


 <section id = 'GRIBloop_input_magml_all_tables'>
   <title>MagML Templates for GRIB Loop Input</title>
   <xi:include href="../paramtables/GribLoop_gribloop_magml_tables.xml"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

    <xi:include href="../paramtables/GribLoop_gribloop_magml_flat_tables.xml"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
</section>


<!--
 <xi:include href="../paramtables/ObsDecoder_bufr_magml_tables.xml"
              xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
  -->

 <section id = 'NetCDF_input_magml_all_tables'>
   <title>MagML Templates for NetCDF Input</title>

   <xi:include href="../paramtables/NetcdfDecoder_netcdf_magml_tables.xml"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

   <xi:include href="../paramtables/NetcdfDecoder_netcdf_magml_flat_tables.xml"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
 </section>

 <!--
 <xi:include href="../paramtables/OdbDecoder_odb_magml_tables.xml"
              xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
  -->
  
 <!--
  <xi:include href="../paramtables/ImportAction_magml_tables.xml"
              xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
  -->
  
 <!--
 <xi:include href="../paramtables/SimplePolylineInput_magml_tables.xml"
              xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
 -->

  <section id="Data_Program_Examples">
    <title>Program Examples</title>

    <para>These examples illustrate the use of the data input
    facilities in <productname>Magics</productname>.</para>
  </section>

  <xi:include href="../examples/manual/xml/data_examples.xml"
              xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />


  <!--
  <xi:include href="../paramtables/data_input_tables.xml"
              xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
  -->

</chapter>
