<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                 "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd"> 

<chapter id="MAGICS_Output_Drivers" label="3">
<title>Magics Output Drivers</title>

  <xi:include href="../phrases/chapterinfo_mod.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />


  <section id="Drivers_Introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>

    <para><productname>Magics</productname> is capable of producing plots in a number of different file
    formats, detailed in the following sections. By default, PostScript output will be produced.</para>
    
    <para>As other parts of <productname>Magics</productname> the code is structured modular to allow 
    easier maintenance and to add easily new output formats. Each module is called a driver and supports 
    at least one output format.</para>

    <para>
    Please be aware that not all output drivers might be installed on your system. Some output drivers dependent on third-party libraries.
    If these are missing at compilation time <productname>Magics++</productname> can not support all formats. 
    Please consult the installation guide for more information.
    </para>

    <para>
    The output drivers have undergone major changes since <productname>MAGICS 6</productname>.
    Please be aware that some default values have changed and are not backwards compatible. For example, 
    in previous versions PostScript output was by default shrunken to 95% of its actual size to be 
    resilient against changes in printer setups. This is not as much as an issue anymore and therefore the default 
    scaling has been set to 100% again.
    </para>

    <para>A special output driver is generating Qt which is only intended for screen display. This driver is 
    used by <productname>Metview</productname> and is not documented further here. 
    </para>

<section id="Output_Parameters">
<title>Controlling the output formats</title>

<para>Parameters can be set to influence how the output formats are generated.
Some parameters are effective on all format, such as file name, and some are 
specific for each format.</para>

<important>
    <title>Magics++</title>
    The interface has been revised to increase consistency and simplify user
    code. The old MAGICS 6 'DEVICE' parameters have been kept for backwards
    compatibility, but the use of the new parameters is strongly recommended.
</important>
</section>

</section>

  <section id="Output_Formats">
    <title>Selecting output formats and their naming</title>

   <para>This section will describe how file formats can be chosen and output names are control
   by <productname>Magics</productname>.</para>

      <para>By default, the output format for a <productname>Magics</productname> plot is
      PostScript (<code>PS</code>).
      You may select a different output format by setting parameter
      <parameter>OUTPUT_FORMAT</parameter> to any of the following:</para>

      <table border="1" id="table_Output_Formats">
        <title>Output Formats</title>
          <tgroup cols="4">
            <colspec colwidth="130" />
            <colspec colwidth="60"  />
            <colspec colwidth="140" />
            <colspec colwidth="90" />
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry align="center">Value</entry>
                <entry align="center">Graphics File Format</entry>
                <entry align="center">Pages</entry>
                <entry align="center">Driver</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>

              <row>
                <entry>PS</entry>
                <entry>vector</entry>
                <entry>produces a single file*</entry>
                <entry>PostScript</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>EPS</entry>
                <entry>vector</entry>
                <entry>produces multiple files</entry>
                <entry>PostScript</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>PDF</entry>
                <entry>vector</entry>
                <entry>produces a single file</entry>
                <entry>Cairo</entry>
              </row>

	      <row>
                <entry>PNG</entry>
                <entry>raster</entry>
                <entry>produces multiple files</entry>
                <entry>Cairo</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>GIF</entry>
                <entry>raster</entry>
                <entry>produces multiple files</entry>
                <entry>GD</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>GIF_ANIMATION</entry>
                <entry>raster</entry>
                <entry>produces a single file</entry>
                <entry>GD</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>JPEG</entry>
                <entry>raster</entry>
                <entry>produces multiple files**</entry>
                <entry>GD</entry>
              </row>

	      <row>
                <entry>SVG</entry>
                <entry>vector</entry>
                <entry>produces multiple files</entry>
                <entry>SVG</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>KML</entry>
                <entry>vector</entry>
                <entry>produces single KMZ file</entry>
                <entry>KML</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
      </table>

      <para>*It is also possible to produce multiple single-page PostScript files, see
      <olink targetdoc="Magics_drivers" targetptr="PostScript_Page_Splitting" />
      below.</para>
      <para>**The JPEG format uses a lossy compression algorithm, resulting in
      lost quality.</para>

      <para>To set in a Fortran program the output format to PNG type:</para>

      <programlisting> 
    CALL <function>PSETC</function> ('<parameter>OUTPUT_FORMAT</parameter>',  'PNG')
      </programlisting>  

      <para>The PostScript based vector formats (PS, EPS, PDF) are the most appropriate for high-quality
      hard-copy printing; the raster formats are more suitable for web pages.
      The SVG driver produces SVG files suitable for interactive
      visualisation or the dynamic generation of raster plots at different scales.
      EPS is a vector format most suited for inclusion in Office and Latex documents.</para>

    <section id="Selecting_Multiple_Output_Formats">
      <title>Selecting Multiple Output Formats</title>

      <para><productname>Magics</productname> can generate plots in multiple output formats simultaneous. 
      For instance, a single <productname>Magics</productname> program can create the same plot in 
      both PostScript and PNG formats in a single run. This approach has a performance advantage over running
      the program separately for each output format as much of the processing is performed
      only once. The parameter to set is <parameter>OUTPUT_FORMATS</parameter> (note the 'S' on the end).
      The following code shows how to set two output devices:</para>

      <table border="1" id="table_Multiple_Output_Formats">
        <title>Selecting Multiple Output Formats</title>
          <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colwidth="70" />
            <colspec colwidth="400" />
            <tbody>

              <row><entry>FORTRAN</entry>
                <entry><programlisting>
    CHARACTER*10 FORMATS
    DIMENSION    FORMATS(2)
    DATA         FORMATS /'PS', 'PNG'/

    CALL <function>POPEN</function>
    CALL <function>PSET1C</function> ('<parameter>OUTPUT_FORMATS</parameter>', FORMATS, 2)
    CALL <function>PSETC</function>  ('<parameter>OUTPUT_NAME</parameter>',    'multiformat')
	  </programlisting></entry>
              </row> 
              <row><entry>C</entry>
                   <entry><programlisting>
    const char *formats [NumFormats] = {"PS", "PNG"};

    <function>mag_open</function>  ();
    <function>mag_set1c</function> ("<parameter>OUTPUT_FORMATS</parameter>", formats, 2);
    <function>mag_setc</function>  ("<parameter>OUTPUT_NAME</parameter>",    "multiformat");
	  </programlisting></entry>
              </row>
     <row><entry>MagML</entry>
                   <entry><programlisting>
   &lt;<classname>drivers</classname>&gt;
      &lt;<classname>ps</classname> <parameter>scale</parameter> = '95' /&gt;
      &lt;<classname>png</classname> /&gt;
   &lt;<classname>drivers</classname>/&gt;
	  </programlisting></entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
      </table>

      <para>For a single-page plot, the above code will produce two files:
      <filename>multiformat.ps</filename> and <filename>multiformat.1.png</filename>.
      The following section explains the file-naming rules in more detail.</para>
    </section>



  <section id="Filenames_Conventions">
    <title>Filenames</title>
    <para>For a single-file plot, as produced by
    <code>PS</code>, <code>PDF</code> and <code>GIF_ANIMATION</code>,
    the default output filename will be <filename>magics.&lt;ext&gt;</filename> 
    where &lt;ext&gt; is replaced by the extension appropriate to the output format.
    For the default format (PostScript) this would produce the file <filename>magics.ps</filename>,
    for animated PNG it would be <filename>magics.png</filename> and so on. The following
    code shows how to change the filename:</para>
    <para></para>
    <programlisting>    CALL <function>PSETC</function> ('<parameter>OUTPUT_NAME</parameter>', 'plot')</programlisting>
    <para></para>

    <para>In this case if the output format is PDF, then the output filename
    will be <filename>plot.pdf</filename> and so on.</para>

    <para>When producing a multiple-file plot, a number is also added to each page,
    although this can be deactivated for the first page. So for instance,
    if the following parameters are set for a three-page plot:</para>


    <table border="1" id="table_Filename_Examples">
      <title>Filename Examples</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colwidth="80" />
          <colspec colwidth="400" />
          <tbody>

            <row><entry>Default</entry>
              <entry><programlisting>
  CALL <function>PSETC</function> ('<parameter>OUTPUT_FORMAT</parameter>', 'PNG')
  CALL <function>PSETC</function> ('<parameter>OUTPUT_NAME</parameter>',   'plot')
	</programlisting>the resultant files will be:
  <programlisting>
        plot.1.png
        plot.2.png
        plot.3.png
</programlisting>Note that even if the plot has only one page and therefore produces
    just one file, the name of that file still obeys the rules in the table above.
 </entry>
            </row> 
            <row><entry>First page numbering OFF</entry>
                 <entry><programlisting>
  CALL <function>PSETC</function> ('<parameter>OUTPUT_FORMAT</parameter>',                 'PNG')
  CALL <function>PSETC</function> ('<parameter>OUTPUT_NAME</parameter>',                   'plot')
  CALL <function>PSETC</function> ('<parameter>OUTPUT_NAME_FIRST_PAGE_NUMBER</parameter>', 'OFF')
	</programlisting>the resultant files will be:
  <programlisting>
        plot.png
        plot.2.png
        plot.3.png
</programlisting></entry>
            </row>

          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
    </table>

    <para>The formatting of the numbers can be modified through the parameter    
    <parameter>OUTPUT_FILE_MINIMAL_WIDTH</parameter>. For instance, setting this to
    <code>2</code> would produce a filename such as <filename>plot.02.png</filename>
    instead of <filename>plot.2.png</filename>.</para>
    
    <para>The character between the root
    and the number can be changed by setting the parameter
    <parameter>OUTPUT_FILE_SEPARATOR</parameter>. For instance, setting this to
    <code>_</code> (underscore) would produce a filename such as <filename>plot_2.png</filename>
    instead of <filename>plot.2.png</filename>.</para>

    <section id="Filenames_Legacy_and_Fine_Control">
      <title>Filenames - Legacy and Fine Control</title>
      
      <para>The above file-naming control should be enough for most purposes
      and is recommended for the most consistent naming of output files.</para>

      <para>However, an extra degree of control is available by not using
      <parameter>OUTPUT_NAME</parameter>, but instead:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>OUTPUT_FULLNAME</parameter> : does not add an extension to the
          supplied filename, instead it needs to be supplied with the file name</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para><parameter>OUTPUT_LEGACY_NAME</parameter> : behaves similar to
          <productname>MAGICS 6</productname> filenaming</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

  </section>


<section id="Common_Drivers_Parameters">
<title>Common parameters for all drivers</title>
<xi:include href="../paramtables/BaseDriver_tables.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
</section>

</section>

<section id="PostScript_Driver">
<title>The PostScript driver</title>

<para>PostScript was developed by Adobe and is still the main format for printers under UNIX. Since traditionally
meteorological maps were aimed for print-outs, PostScript is historically the default
output of <productname>Magics</productname>. No third-party library is required 
to generate PostScript files and the driver is always available to users.</para>

<section id="PostScript_Page_Splitting">
<title>Page Splitting</title>
<para>By default, a multi-page plot will result in a single output file containing
    those multiple pages. It is possible to alter this behaviour by setting
    the <parameter>OUTPUT_PS_SPLIT</parameter> parameter:</para>

 <programlisting>
    CALL <function>PSETC</function> ('<parameter>OUTPUT_PS_SPLIT</parameter>', 'ON')
 </programlisting>
	
    <para>When this is set, each page will be plotted to a new PostScript file,
    following the filenaming rules in the table above.</para>

    <important> <title>Magics++</title>
      <para>This behaviour differs from previous versions of
      <productname>Magics</productname> where the environment variable
      <envar>PS_SPLIT</envar> was used instead of a
      <productname>Magics</productname> parameter.</para>
    </important>
   </section>

<section id="PostScript_Page_Scaling">
    <title>Page Scaling</title>
    
    <para>Even though printers support standardised page sizes, such as A4 and A3, they 
    often are not able to print on the full page. Depending on the printer an border 
    area surrounding the page can not be printed on. This needs to be kept in mind if 
    designing maps to be printed. To help with this <productname>Magics</productname>
    provides an option to shrink/rescale a PostScript page to fit to the printer.</para>
    
    <important> <title>Magics++</title>
    In previous versions PostScript output was by default shrunken to 95% of its actual size to be 
    resilient against changes in printer setups. This is not an issue anymore and therefore the default 
    scaling has been set to 100% again. Please use '<parameter>OUTPUT_PS_SCALE</parameter>' and set 
    it to '0.95' if this kind of scaling is still required.
    </important>
   </section>

  <section id="Generating_EPS_output">
  <title>EPS</title>

      <para>The EPS file format does not support multiple pages, so if a
      multi-page plot is created in EPS format, multiple files are generated
      using the rules above, as if '<parameter>OUTPUT_PS_SPLIT</parameter>' is on. EPS is best if maps need to be used within <productname>Word</productname> and <productname>Latex</productname> documents.
      </para>
  </section>

  <xi:include href="../paramtables/PostScript_tables.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

  <section id = 'PostScriptDriver_magml_all_tables'>
    <title>MagML Templates for PostScript Output</title>

    <xi:include href="../paramtables/PostScriptDriver_ps_magml_tables.xml"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
<!--
    <xi:include href="../paramtables/PostScriptDriver_ps_magml_flat_tables.xml"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
-->
  </section>
</section>  <!-- End of PS -->


<section id="SVG_Driver">
<title>The SVG driver</title>

<para>
This output driver produces vector graphics in the SVG format as defined by the W3C. The 
SVG output can be viewed by many web browsers directly (Firefox, Opera, Safari) or can be 
viewed within Internet Explorer, with the help of a plug-in, such as the Renesis Player, 
or a JavaScript library, such as SVGWeb. 
SVG is also used by many graphics programs as input format (Inkscape or Adobe Illustrator). 
SVG is not only a static format, but also allows for interactivity. This is used by <productname>Magics</productname> 
to optionally implement features such as the toggling of layers.
</para>

<para>
By default the generated maps are scalable. This means that the image is rendered according 
to the viewers size. If the user changes the size of the browser window also the image is 
rescaled to fit in. In many viewers, such as Firefox, the key combination '<keysym>Crtl +</keysym>',
'<keysym>Crtl -</keysym>' and '<keysym>Crtl 0</keysym>' allows to zoom in/out of a SVG graphics.
</para>

<para>
Since SVG is based on XML it is, to a degree, human readable and can also be parsed by search engines. 
As with all XML derived formats, SVG allows the processing through various XML technologies, such 
as XSLT or the manipulation through JavaScript (AJAX).
</para>

<para>
On the web server side there is a <productname>Batik</productname>, a Java-based toolkit for 
applications or applets that want to use images in the SVG format for various purposes, such 
as display, generation or manipulation.
</para>
<!--
  <section id="Interactivity_in_SVG">  <title>Interactivity in SVG</title>
  <para>
  All SVG files produced by <productname>Magics</productname> have
        basic interactivity by default. Typing '<keysym>c</keysym>' or
        '<keysym>C</keysym>' (browser-dependent) toggles coastlines on and off.
        Typing '<keysym>d</keysym>' or '<keysym>D</keysym>' toggles the hi/low
        text in the drawing area. Clicking on the ID line opens the external
        <productname>Magics</productname> web page is opened. These features are
        simply demonstrations of what is possible; more sophisticated features
        will be implemented in the next version of <productname>Magics</productname>.
  </para>
  </section>
-->
  <section id="Serving_SVG"><title>SVG served on the web</title>
  <para>
  On most web servers SVG can be used like any other graphics file format.
  However, sometimes SVG and especially its compressed form of SVGZ are not configured correctly on
  web servers. To serve SVG and SVGZ files correctly you should have following lines added to your 
  <filename>.htaccess</filename> file (on Apache servers):
  </para>
    <programlisting>
AddType image/svg+xml svg svgz
AddEncoding gzip svgz
    </programlisting>
  </section>

  <para>For more information on SVG, please have the look at following resources:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><ulink url="http://www.w3.org/Graphics/SVG/">W3C - SVG standard</ulink></listitem>
      <listitem><ulink url="http://xmlgraphics.apache.org/batik/">Apache - Batik</ulink></listitem>
      <listitem><ulink url="http://code.google.com/p/svgweb/">SVGweb - Javascript module to view SVG in Internet Explorer</ulink></listitem>
 <!--     <listitem><ulink url="http://www.examotion.com">Renesis Player for Internet Explorer</ulink></listitem>  -->
      <listitem><ulink url="http://www.inkscape.org/">Inkscape - SVG editor</ulink></listitem>
      <listitem><ulink url="http://code.google.com/p/svg-edit/">Web based SVG editor</ulink></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <xi:include href="../paramtables/SVG_tables.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

  <section id = 'SVGDriver_magml_all_tables'>
    <title>MagML Templates for SVG Output</title>
    <xi:include href="../paramtables/SVGDriver_svg_magml_tables.xml"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
<!--
    <xi:include href="../paramtables/SVGDriver_svg_magml_flat_tables.xml"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
-->
  </section>

</section>


<section id="Cairo_Driver">
<title>The Cairo driver (PDF, EPS, PNG)</title>

<para>This driver uses the <productname>Cairo</productname> graphics library to 
generate various output formats. The library is quite new and might not be installed 
on older or non-mainstream systems. However the situation is improving with <productname>Firefox</productname>
and <productname>Inkscape</productname> requiring Cairo being installed. Cairo works 
internally with vectors and produces high quality output.
</para>

<section id="Cairo_pdf">
   <title>Cairo's vector output - PDF, CAIRO_PS, CAIRO_EPS, CAIRO_SVG</title>
   <para>Cairo produces high quality vector outputs. However there are some disadvantages: CAIRO_PS and CAIRO_EPS
   support only <parameter>RGB</parameter> (not <parameter>CYMK</parameter>) and <parameter>CAIRO_SVG</parameter> are non-scalable and do not support interactivity. 
   Therefore it is still recommended to use <parameter>PS</parameter> and <parameter>EPS</parameter> (from PostScript driver) and <parameter>SVG</parameter> (from SVG driver).</para>
</section>

<section id="Cairo_png">
   <title>Cairo's raster output - PNG</title>
   <para>The Cairo driver offers <parameter>PNG</parameter> as a raster output. This output is intended for use on web pages.
   PNG output has two extra feature compared to the other outputs: possible 
   transparent background and the return of meta information about the plot inside the PNG.
   Both features are intended for when PNGs are used for web pages. The transparent overlay 
   allows overlays of multiple images. The meta information generated by Magics++ allows 
   JavaScript developer navigate the PNG and implement interactions on top of the PNGs content.</para>
</section>

<section id="Cairo_screen">
   <title>Cairo's screen dump - X</title>
   <para>The Cairo driver can also be used do visualise a plot directly on the screen 
   setting the format to <parameter>X</parameter>.</para>
</section>

<section id="Cairo_context">
   <title>Setting your own Cairo context [Advanced]</title>

   <para>In some cases it might be useful to hand <productname>Magics</productname>
   an own Cairo graphics context. This might be useful if the Magics Program wants to access directly 
   Cairo and add its own drawing operations to be displayed in a separate widget.</para>

  <table border="1" id="cairo_context">
        <title>Handing cairo an own context</title>
          <tgroup cols="1">
            <colspec colwidth="450" />
            <tbody>
              <row>
                 <entry><programlisting>
   ...
   cr = cairo_create(surface);
   ...
   mag_open();
   mag_setc("output_format","cairo");
   mag_setp("output_cairo_drawing_context", cr);
   ...
</programlisting></entry>
</row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
      </table>
 </section>

<para>For more information on Cairo, see the documentation at:</para>

   <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
	<ulink url="http://www.cairographics.org">Cairo home page</ulink>
     </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>

  <xi:include href="../paramtables/Cairo_tables.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

<!--

 <section id = 'CairoDriver_magml_all_tables'>
   <title>MagML Templates for usage of the Cairo driver</title>
    <xi:include href="../paramtables/CairoDriver_png_magml_tables.xml"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

    <xi:include href="../paramtables/CairoDriver_png_magml_flat_tables.xml"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

    <xi:include href="../paramtables/CairoDriver_pdf_magml_tables.xml"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

    <xi:include href="../paramtables/CairoDriver_pdf_magml_flat_tables.xml"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
 </section>
 -->

</section>


<section id="KML">
<title>The KML driver (KMZ/KML) [new]</title>

 <para>KML is an XML-based file format used to display describe vector data in a geospatial browser,
  such as <productname>Google Earth</productname>, <productname>Google Maps</productname>, and 
  <productname>Microsoft Virtual Earth</productname>. KML is very 
  different from the others formats supported in <productname>Magics</productname>. Even though it is 
  a vector format it has dimensions for expressing height and time (for animations).
  The height is expressed in kilometres, not pressure levels, and is set through a parameter for all data.
  Different layers of information can be stored and controlled by the Google Earth user interface. 
 </para>
      
 <para>KML uses often external (raster) files to optimise the file size. In case of <productname>Magics</productname>, it 
  uses PNG files to express cell shading and satellite data. The <productname>Magics</productname> logo is also stored in 
  a external file. Therefore <productname>Magics</productname> generates zip archives of all generated files (KML, PNGs and logo) 
  in the so-called KMZ files. The resulting KMZ files can be read by all KML readers and the GNU zip tools (you might want to change 
  the files extension to .zip first).
 </para>
      
 <para>
  Please be aware that KML does not support all forms of display offered by <productname>Magics</productname>. 
  For example graph plotting is not supported in KML. Colours might also need 
  adjusting, since <productname>Google Earth</productname>'s background is generally darker compared 
  to the white (paper) background of other <productname>Magics</productname> output formats.
 </para>
 
 <para> 
  <productname>Magics</productname> offers parameters to give meta information, such as author and 
  descriptions and an initial focus point. 
 </para>
      
 <para>
  Please be further aware that KML currently does only generate valid output for cylindrical and 
  Mercator projection. This is because KML's co-ordinate system is based on Longitude/Latitude. For
  projections different to the mentioned above a different co-ordinate system is used inside 
  <productname>Magics</productname>.   
 </para>
      
 <para>For more information on Google Earth, see the documentation at:</para>

   <itemizedlist>
     <listitem><ulink url="http://earth.google.com">Google Earth</ulink></listitem>
   </itemizedlist>

  <xi:include href="../paramtables/KML_tables.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

 <section id = 'KMLDriver_magml_all_tables'>
   <title>MagML Templates for KML Output</title>
   <xi:include href="../paramtables/KMLDriver_kml_magml_tables.xml"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
<!--
   <xi:include href="../paramtables/KMLDriver_kml_magml_flat_tables.xml"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
-->
 </section>

</section>


<section id="GD_Driver">
<title>The GD driver (PNG,GIF,JPEG)</title>

  <para>The GD driver provides output in various raster formats. The used GD library is more 
   lightweight but also lower quality than the Cairo library.
  </para>

 <section id="Generating_an_animated_GIF">
 <title>Generating an Animated GIF</title>

  <para>In order to obtain an animated GIF image as output, you should use the format
   <code>GIF_ANIMATION</code>. In this case, you may set the delay between pages of the
   animation by setting the parameter <parameter>OUTPUT_GIF_DELAY</parameter> to a value
   representing a time-scale in 100ths of a second. For instance, to create an animated
   GIF called animated_plot.gif with a delay of half a second between pages, use the
   following code:</para>
   
        <programlisting>
    CALL <function>PSETC</function> ('<parameter>OUTPUT_FORMAT</parameter>',    'GIF_ANIMATION')
    CALL <function>PSETI</function> ('<parameter>OUTPUT_GIF_DELAY</parameter>',  50)
    CALL <function>PSETC</function> ('<parameter>OUTPUT_NAME</parameter>',      'animated_plot')
        </programlisting>	

        <tip>
          <para>Note that animated GIF images are not properly supported by
          <application>xv</application> and <application>display</application>. Therefore, 
	  in order to view your GIF animation correctly, a web browser such as 
	  <application>Firefox</application>, <application>Internet Explorer</application> or
          <application>Konqueror</application> should be used. Also note that
          <application>xv</application> does not support PNG on many platforms
          very well. You can use <application>display</application>
          to view PNG files properly.</para>
        </tip>
      </section>
<!--
   <section id="Raster_Output_In_MagML">
        <title>Raster Output In MagML</title>
        <para>The following example illustrates the MagML elements required to generate raster output
        from a MagML program; their attributes are set here to their default values.</para>

        <programlisting>
      &lt;<classname>drivers</classname>&gt;
        &lt;<classname>gif</classname> <parameter>xml</parameter> = 'OFF' /&gt;

        &lt;<classname>gif_animation</classname> <parameter>gif_delay</parameter> = '100'
                       <parameter>xml</parameter> = 'OFF' /&gt;

        &lt;<classname>png</classname> <parameter>png_transparent</parameter> = 'OFF'
             <parameter>xml</parameter> = 'OFF' /&gt;
      &lt;<classname>drivers</classname>/&gt;
        </programlisting>
  </section>
-->
  <xi:include href="../paramtables/GD_tables.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />


<!--
  <section id = 'GDDriver_magml_all_tables'>
   <title>MagML Templates for GD related output</title>
   <xi:include href="../paramtables/GDDriver_kml_magml_tables.xml"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

   <xi:include href="../paramtables/GDDriver_kml_magml_flat_tables.xml"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
  </section>
-->
</section>

</chapter>
