<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
(C) Copyright 1996-2016 ECMWF.

This software is licensed under the terms of the Apache Licence Version 2.0
which can be obtained at http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0. 
In applying this licence, ECMWF does not waive the privileges and immunities 
granted to it by virtue of its status as an intergovernmental organisation nor
does it submit to any jurisdiction.
-->

<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                 "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd"> 
<chapter id="Overview" label="1">
  <title>Overview</title>

  <xi:include href="../phrases/chapterinfo_mod.xml"
              xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

  <section id="Overview_Introduction">
    <title>Introduction to Magics</title>

    <para>The Meteorological Applications Graphics Integrated Colour System
    (<productname>MAGICS</productname>) is a software system that permits the
    plotting of contours, wind fields, observations, satellite images,
    symbols, <remark>streamlines, isotachs, </remark>text, axis and graphs <remark>and pie charts</remark>.

    <productname>Magics</productname> is developed by the Meteorological Visualisation Section at <orgname>ECMWF</orgname> 
    and is used to generate many of its plots - on the
    web, in the MetOps room, for data monitoring and verification. <productname>Magics</productname>
    is the graphics engine used in <orgname>ECMWF</orgname>'s meteorological workstation Metview and 
    <orgname>Meteo-France</orgname>'s Synergie meteorological workstation. It is used within many
    <orgname>ECMWF</orgname>'s Member States and other organisations around the world.</para>

    <para><remark><productname>Magics</productname> contouring is based on
    CONICON, developed by the University of Bath in the United Kingdom. Linear
    contouring is also available.</remark></para>

    <para><remark><productname>Magics</productname> observation plotting is
    based on a package developed by <remark>the Meteorological services of
    Denmark and</remark> Sweden. <productname>Magics</productname> streamline plotting is based on an
    algorithm supplied by Florida State University, Florida,
    USA.</remark></para>

    <para><productname>Magics</productname> is meteorological oriented and forecasts and analysis fields may be read in various formats, for
    instance GRIB and NetCDF. Observations can be read from BUFR files or retrieved from an ODB
    database. For more details, see <olink targetdoc="Magics_data" targetptr="Data_Input" />.</para>

    <para>The following diagram shows the top-level architecture of <productname>Magics++</productname>:</para>
<para/>
<para/>

    <mediaobject id="magics_architecture_diagram">
      <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="../diagrams/Magics_overview.png" format="PNG" width="14cm" align="center" />
      </imageobject>

      <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="images/diagrams/Magics_overview.png" format="PNG" width="500" align="center" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

  </section>

    <section id="History">
      <title>MAGICS History</title>

      <para>The first pre-release of <productname>MAGICS</productname>,
      version 0.3, was released as a FORTRAN library in July 1985 on a trial
      basis. This release contained facilities for plot layout as well as
      contouring, coastlines and text headings. At the same time the first
      versions of the
      <productname><productname>MAGICS</productname></productname> manuals
      were released. With minor enhancements, this version became operational
      in December 1985. The first full release of
      <productname><productname>MAGICS</productname></productname>, version
      1.0, became available in December 1987 and incorporated many new
      features. Subsequent releases have introduced extra features as they
      became available, such as linear contouring, axis plotting, streamlines
      and isotachs, graph and pie charts, symbol plotting and satellite image
      plotting.</para>
      <para>Development of <productname>MAGICS 6</productname> was frozen in 2008;
      development of <productname>Magics++</productname> started in 2004.</para>
    </section>
 
    <section id="Current_Release">
      <title>Magics++</title>

      <para><productname>Magics++</productname> represents a
      complete re-write of the <productname>Magics</productname> source code.
      Whereas previous versions were
      written mainly in FORTRAN with some C++ code for the output drivers,
      <productname>Magics++</productname> is written entirely in C++. This development makes
      <productname>Magics</productname> more flexible, allowing new features
      to be added more easily. Although <productname>Magics++</productname> is
      intended to be as backwardly compatible as possible with the previous
      Fortran interface, there are new ways of doing some things - these will be
      highlighted in the text of this manual with the following notation:</para>

      <important> <title>Magics++</title>This is new to, or has been changed in Magics++.</important>

      <para>Perhaps the biggest change is that
      <productname>Magics</productname> is no longer just a FORTRAN library.
      Plot descriptions can now also be written in an XML-based format called
      <firstterm>MagML</firstterm> and programs can now also be written in
      C and Python.</para>

      <para><productname>Magics</productname> can now read data from a wider
      variety of sources.<!-- Notably, data from an ODB database can be retrieved
      and plotted from within a <productname>Magics</productname> program (see
      <olink targetdoc="Magics_data" targetptr="ODB_Input" />).-->
      NetCDF data is supported (see
      <olink targetdoc="Magics_data" targetptr="NetCDF_Data_Input" />).
      By using the new GRIB_API library, <productname>Magics</productname>
      is able to read GRIB 2 files as well as GRIB 1 files.
      Note that <productname>Magics</productname> currently does not support 
     interpolation of grids - all GRIB data must be in regular or reduced Gaussian or Lat/Long grid.
<remark>
WHEN WILL WE HAVE INTERPOLATION?
</remark>
</para>

      <para>The output drivers have also been expanded. PostScript remains,
      and in addition there are drivers that can produce plots in PDF, EPS,
      PNG, GIF and SVG formats amongst others. <productname>Magics</productname>
      now has the ability to produce multiple outputs from a single program by
      using multiple drivers 'simultaneously', delivering significant speed
      benefits over using an external tool to convert PostScript output or
      running a program twice to produce different outputs.</para>

      <para>The CONICON contouring package formerly used by
      <productname>Magics</productname> has been replaced with a method using
      the Akima interpolation algorithms. By default,
      <productname>Magics</productname> will try to choose a level of
      interpolation that gives good quality results without sacrificing
      performance; the user can also set the interpolation level manually if
      needed. Linear contouring is still available.</para>

      <para>The user now has more flexibility in determining the resolution of
      coastlines used in plots. <productname>Magics++</productname> comes with
      higher resolution coastline files than previous versions but uses
      lower-resolution files where appropriate in order to save time and
      reduce the size of the output file; this behaviour is
      user-configurable. These coastline files now include basic
      support for rivers and lakes.</para>

      <para><remark>Legend? Text &amp; annotation?</remark></para>
 
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="http://www.ecmwf.int/publications/manuals/magics/">Magics webpage</ulink></para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="http://www.ecmwf.int/publications/manuals/magics/magplus/docs/Magics++_Newsletter_110_Article.pdf">Magics++ Overview</ulink></para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
        <para><ulink url="http://www.ecmwf.int/publications/manuals/magics/magplus/docs/Magics++_Newsletter_122_Article.pdf">Magics++ 2.8 - New developments</ulink></para>
     </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>

 </section>

  <section id="MAGICS Features">
    <title>Magics Features</title>

      <para>Magics contains many powerful features:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Comprehensive list of simple English language parameters</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Extensive use of colour</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Flexible programming interface (API) for multiple languages (Fortran, C, Python, XML)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Selection of geographical area and direct projection of
          data</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Matrix, GRIB, BUFR, ODB and NetCDF data input(see <olink targetdoc="Magics_data" targetptr="Data_Input" />)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Coastline rendering with automatic quality-selection for
          high quality with minimal output file size.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>High quality contouring based on Akima interpolation and lower
          quality linear contouring (see <olink targetdoc="Magics_contour" targetptr="Contouring"/>) </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Shading between contour lines</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Wind fields directly projected, as arrows or WMO flags (see <olink targetdoc="Magics_wind" targetptr="Wind_Plotting" />)</para>
        </listitem>

        <remark>
        <listitem>
          <para>Streamline and Isotach plotting</para>
        </listitem>
        </remark>

        <listitem>
          <para>Observation plotting <!-- (see <olink targetdoc="Magics_obs" targetptr="ObservationPlotting" />) --></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Graph and Axis plotting, with advanced features such as Boxplots</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Symbol plotting</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Satellite image plotting</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>High quality text plotting (see <olink targetdoc="Magics_text" targetptr="Text_Plotting" />)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Advanced legend plotting</para>
        </listitem>

      </itemizedlist>

   </section>


    <section id="Overview_Page_Layout">
      <title>Page Layout</title>

      <para>To make the positioning of user's plots simple,
      <productname>Magics</productname> has introduced the concepts of
      subpage, page and super-page.</para>

      <para>A super-page corresponds to the plotting area to be used on a
      plotting device. With the plot layout facilities, pages can be
      positioned automatically or by the user inside the super-page.
      Similarly, one or more subpages can be plotted inside a page.</para>

      <para>Page Layout is fully described in
      <olink targetdoc="Magics_layout_mapping_coastlines" targetptr="Layout_Mapping_and_Coastlines" />.</para>
    </section>


    <section id="Overview_Programming_Concepts">
      <title>Programming Interfaces</title>

      <para>A typical FORTRAN <productname>Magics</productname> program
      consists of a series of parameter-setting, action and pseudo action
      routines. The parameters required by an action routine should be set, if
      required, before that action routine is called.</para>

      <para>An alternative, XML-based plot description language is also available.
      It is called <firstterm>MagML</firstterm> and permits simple yet powerful plot
      descriptions to be used to generate plots without the need for a compile/link
      cycle.</para>

      <para>The programming interfaces offered by <productname>Magics</productname> are
      fully described in <olink targetdoc="Magics_using" targetptr="Using_MAGICS"/>.</para>
    </section>

</chapter>
