<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                 "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd"> 
<chapter id="Wind_Plotting" label="7">
  <title>Wind Plotting</title>

  <xi:include href="../phrases/chapterinfo_mod.xml"
              xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

  <section id="Wind_Introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>Wind plotting facilities allow users to plot wind and wind related
    parameters as follows:</para>

    <para>Wind fields may be presented to Magics in matrix form, as U/V
    velocity components or as speed/direction components. Wind fields may also
    be passed in GRIB code data as U/V or speed/direction<remark> or
    vorticity/divergence</remark>. These wind fields may be plotted in one of two
    ways:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Wind arrows; represented by a vector whose length is
        proportional to the speed of the wind.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>WMO standard wind flags; represented by barbs and solid
        pennants.</para>
      </listitem>

      <remark><listitem>
        <para>Streamlines; a line that is everywhere tangential to the
        instantaneous wind vectors.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Isotachs; a contour line of wind speed.</para>
      </listitem></remark>
    </itemizedlist>

    <remark><para>Wind arrow and wind flag plotting are described in this chapter.
    Streamline and isotach plotting are described in Chapter VIII- Streamline
    / Isotach Plotting .</para></remark>

<remark>
    <para>Magics also permits wind related parameters, which are generated
    from differential properties of the wind field, to be plotted using normal
    contouring facilities. These related parameters are Divergence, Vorticity,
    Stream Functions and Velocity Potential.</para>
</remark>

    <para>Fields other than recognised wind fields (u/v<remark>, vorticity/divergence</remark>
    and speed/direction) may be plotted as wind vectors;
    <olink targetdoc="Magics_wind" targetptr="Wind_Data_Input" />
    describes how to achieve this.</para>
    
    <!--
    <important id="Vorticity_Devergence_on_Gridpoints"> <title>Magics++</title>
    <productname>Magics++</productname> now permits the plotting of
    vorticity/divergence wind fields stored in grid points; this was not
    possible under <productname>MAGICS 6</productname>.</important>
    -->

  </section>

  <section id="Wind_Data_Input">
    <title>Data Input</title>

    <para>To plot a wind field, users may pass the wind component fields
    either in GRIB code format or in matrix form, each component field being
    in a separate matrix.</para>

    <section id="Wind_GRIB_Code">
      <title>GRIB Code</title>

      <para>To pass the wind components in GRIB format, the name (including
      the path) of the file containing the components should be passed as
      follows:</para>
      <programlisting>
    CALL <function>PSETC</function>('<parameter>GRIB_INPUT_FILE_NAME</parameter>', 'wind_data').
      </programlisting>
      <para>The position of
      the wind components on the file should be indicated as follows:</para>

      <remark>
        <para>Diagram 1 here</para>
      </remark>

      <programlisting>
    CALL <function>PSETI</function> ('<parameter>GRIB_WIND_POSITION_1</parameter>',N)
    CALL <function>PSETI</function> ('<parameter>GRIB_WIND_POSITION_2</parameter>',M)
      </programlisting>

<para>where N and M are the positions (record numbers on the file).</para>

      <para>When passing GRIB code data, it is possible to pass fields other
      than recognised wind fields (u/v<remark>, vorticity/divergence</remark> and
      speed/direction) to Magics and request that they are plotted as wind
      fields. To achieve this, the parameter
      <parameter>GRIB_WIND_MODE</parameter> should be set by the user to
      specify which way the input fields are to be interpolated, i.e. as u/v<remark>,
      vorticity/divergence</remark> or strength/direction. The valid values are
      '<code>UV</code>' (default) , '<code>VD</code>' and '<code>SD</code>'.
      Following is an example of setting
      <parameter>GRIB_WIND_MODE</parameter> :</para>

      <programlisting>
    CALL <function>PSETC</function> ('<parameter>GRIB_WIND_MODE</parameter>','UV')
      </programlisting>

      <para>The fields should be passed to Magics in the usual way, as if they
      were recognised wind fields, e.g.</para>

      <programlisting>
    CALL <function>PSETC</function> ('<parameter>GRIB_INPUT_FILE_NAME</parameter>','wind_data')
    CALL <function>PSETI</function> ('<parameter>GRIB_WIND_POSITION_1</parameter>', 1)
    CALL <function>PSETI</function> ('<parameter>GRIB_WIND_POSITION_2</parameter>', 2).
      </programlisting>

      <remark>
      <para>It is possible to have the two fields necessary for wind
      plotting, in two different input files. If this is the case, the
      parameter <parameter>GRIB_INPUT_FILE_NAME</parameter>
      should be used to pass one of the file names and
      <parameter>GRIB_INPUT_FILE_NAME</parameter> should be used to pass the
      second file name. The parameter
      <parameter>GRIB_INPUT_FILE_NUMBER</parameter> must be set to
      '<code>TWO</code>' , the default being '<code>ONE</code>' .</para>
      </remark>

      <para>For further information concerning GRIB code data, see
      <olink targetdoc="Magics_data" targetptr="Data_Input" />.</para>

    </section>


    <section id="Wind_Matrix_Data">
      <title>Matrix Data</title>

      <para>Input field parameters, as described in
      <olink targetdoc="Magics_data" targetptr="Data_Input" />, must be used to
      describe the organisation of the data in the matrices. After the
      relevant parameters are properly set, the wind data may be passed in the
      following way:</para>

      <para>For u and v components:</para>

      <programlisting>
    CALL <function>PSET2R</function> ('<parameter>INPUT_WIND_U_COMPONENT</parameter>',ARRAY1,M,N)
    CALL <function>PSET2R</function> ('<parameter>INPUT_WIND_V_COMPONENT</parameter>',ARRAY2,M,N)
      </programlisting>
      <para>For wind speed and direction:</para>

      <programlisting>
    CALL <function>PSET2R</function> ('<parameter>INPUT_WIND_SPEED</parameter>',ARRAY1,M,N)
    CALL <function>PSET2R</function> ('<parameter>INPUT_WIND_DIRECTION</parameter>',ARRAY2,M,N)
      </programlisting>

      <remark>
      <para>For wind speed when plotting isotachs only:</para>

      <programlisting>
    CALL <function>PSET2R</function> ('<parameter>INPUT_WIND_SPEED</parameter>',ARRAY1,M,N)
      </programlisting>
      </remark>

      <para>where all arrays must be dimensioned as <code>ARRAY(M,N)</code> in
      the calling program.</para>

      <para>The units of <parameter>INPUT_WIND_U_COMPONENT</parameter> ,
      <parameter>INPUT_WIND_V_COMPONENT</parameter> and
      <parameter>INPUT_WIND_SPEED</parameter> are metres per second. Those of
      <parameter>INPUT_WIND_DIRECTION</parameter> are degrees measured in an
      anticlockwise direction from the eastern point of the compass.</para>
    </section>
  </section>


  <section id="Wind_Plotting_Methods">
    <title>Plotting Methods</title>

    <para>To plot a wind field, the action routine <function>PWIND</function>
    must be called. The type of wind plot required is indicated by setting the
    parameter <parameter>WIND_FIELD_TYPE</parameter> to one of the following
    values, the default value being '<code>ARROWS</code>'.</para>

    <para>'<code>ARROWS</code>' : The speed and direction of the wind is
    plotted using an arrow whose length is proportional to the speed of the
    wind and whose orientation is in the direction of the wind at the grid
    position.</para>

    <para>'<code>FLAGS</code>' : Will plot the speed and direction of the wind
    using the WMO standard wind flags representation (barbs and solid
    pennants).</para>

    <remark><para>'<code>STREAMLINES</code>' : Will plot streamlines tangential to the
    instantaneous wind vectors.</para></remark>
  </section>

  <section id="Wind_Field_Projection">
    <title>Wind Field Projection</title>

    <para><productname>Magics</productname> will automatically project the wind field from the regular
    input field onto the requested projection. In the cases of wind flags and
    wind arrows, each flag or arrow will be directly projected, taking the
    necessary rotation into consideration. This means that wind arrows and
    wind flags will be plotted along lines of latitude and longitude on polar
    stereographic maps and not in columns and rows. No interpolation is
    performed during the projection. A thinning procedure may be applied to
    wind flags and arrows close to the poles.</para>

    <para>It should be noted that cylindrical projection is not
    angle-conformal, which means that the angle of the wind arrows or flags is
    not conserved in this projection. It is advisable not to use cylindrical
    projection for wind plotting outside the tropics.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="Wind_Field_Thinning">
    <title>Wind Field Thinning</title>

    <para>In some cases, wind arrows (and wind flags) may overlap. This
    depends on the length of the arrows or flags, the grid size of the input
    matrix and on the size of the subpage. With a polar stereographic
    projection, the distance between projected grid points will be smaller at
    higher latitudes. Therefore on polar stereographic projections for grid
    points close to the pole, a thinning procedure will be automatically
    applied to latitudes above 60 degrees.</para>

    <para>The parameter <parameter>WIND_THINNING_FACTOR</parameter> controls
    the thinning of wind fields plotted in different projections. For
    Cylindrical, Mercator and Satellite projections, for which there is no
    automatic thinning, the thinning factor corresponds to the rounded up
    value of the parameter <parameter>WIND_THINNING_FACTOR</parameter>. For a
    factor rounded to N, every Nth grid point in both X and Y directions, is
    plotted, e.g. the statement :</para>

    <programlisting>
    CALL <function>PSETR</function>('<parameter>WIND_THINNING_FACTOR</parameter>', 2.6)</programlisting>

    <para>will cause Magics to plot wind flags or wind arrows for every third
    grid point value in the input matrix, in both the X and Y directions.</para>

    <para>For Polar Stereographic projections, the thinning factor is the
    distance, in both X and Y directions, corresponding to the projected
    <parameter>INPUT_FIELD_LONGITUDE_STEP</parameter>, along 60 degrees
    latitude, multiplied by the value of
    <parameter>WIND_THINNING_FACTOR</parameter> . After plotting at a grid
    point, all subsequent grid points, whose distance from the current grid
    point is less than the thinning factor, will be ignored. The default value
    is <code>2.0</code>, e.g. the statement :</para>

    <programlisting>
    CALL <function>PSETR</function>('<parameter>WIND_THINNING_FACTOR</parameter>', 1.0)</programlisting>

    <para>will cause Magics to plot wind flags or wind arrows with no thinning
    until 60 degree latitude. Above the 60 degree latitude, thinning will be
    applied automatically.</para>

    <para>For all projections, if <parameter>WIND_THINNING_FACTOR</parameter>
    has the value <code>0.0</code>, no thinning will be applied. This also
    means that the automatic thinning is not applied in polar stereographic.
    <remark>In the case of streamlines, this thinning procedure is not applied.
    Chapter VIII- Streamline / Isotach Plotting for details concerning
    streamline thinning.</remark></para>
  </section>


  <section id="Plotting_Wind_Flags">
    <title>Plotting Wind Flags</title>

    <para>Wind fields comprising U and V components or speed and direction,
    may be plotted with WMO standard wind flags.</para>

    <para>A wind flag is represented by barbs and solid pennants, a full barb
    representing a wind speed of 5 m/s, a half barb representing a wind speed
    of 2.5 m/s, and a pennant representing a wind speed of 25 m/s. All barbs
    and pennants lie to the left of the wind shaft in the Northern hemisphere
    and to the right of the wind shaft in the Southern hemisphere. The wind
    flag points towards the direction the wind is coming from.</para>

    <section id="Wind_Flags_Unit_Length">
      <title>Unit Length</title>

      <para>The default length of the wind flag shaft is 1.0 centimetre. The
      parameter <parameter>WIND_FLAG_LENGTH</parameter> may be used to set
      another length (in centimetres).</para>
    </section>

    <!-- NOT IMPLEMENTED yet as of 18/01/2007
    <section id="Wind_Flag_Mode">
      <title>Wind Flag Mode</title>

      <para>The parameter <parameter>WIND_FLAG_MODE</parameter> controls how
      the wind flag shaft will be drawn. If
      <parameter>WIND_FLAG_MODE</parameter> is set to '<code>NORMAL</code>'
      the shaft of the wind flag will be drawn with a solid line, which is the
      default. If set to '<code>OFF_LEVEL</code>' or '<code>OFF_TIME</code>'
      the wind flags will be drawn with dashed lines as described
      below.</para>
      </remark>

      <remark>
        <para>Diagram 2!</para>
      </remark>

      <remark>
      <para>When winds are plotted on the same map at two different vertical
      levels, it is possible to distinguish them from each other by drawing
      the entire wind shaft as dashed lines (<code>OFF_LEVEL</code> ).</para>

      <para>When winds are plotted at "different times", it is possible to
      distinguish them from each other by drawing the wind shaft with dashed
      lines as far as the barbs and pennants (<code>OFF_TIME</code>).</para>
      </remark>
    </section>
    -->

    <section id="Wind_Flags_Plot_Suppression">
      <title>Plot Suppression</title>

      <para>To suppress the plotting of wind flags above and below certain
      wind speed values, the parameters
      <parameter>WIND_FLAG_MAX_SPEED</parameter> and
      <parameter>WIND_FLAG_MIN_SPEED</parameter> may be used. The default
      values of these parameters are set to very high and very low,
      respectively, so that all wind speeds will be plotted.</para>

      <remark>
      <para>The parameter <parameter>WIND_FLAG_CROSS_BOUNDARY</parameter>
      controls the plotting of wind flags on and outside the subpage boundary.
      It may be set to '<code>ON</code>' or '<code>OFF</code>' . When set to
      '<code>ON</code>' (default) wind flags are not plotted on or outside the
      boundary.</para>
      </remark>
    </section>

    <section id="Wind_Flags_Origin_Markers">
      <title>Origin Markers</title>

      <para>The origin point may be plotted in various ways. The parameter
      <parameter>WIND_FLAG_ORIGIN_MARKER</parameter> controls this feature. It
      can take three values, '<code>CIRCLE</code>' , '<code>DOT</code>' or
      '<code>OFF</code>' .</para>

      <para>'<code>CIRCLE</code>' (default) : will plot a circle around the
      origin point and the wind flag shaft will start at the perimeter of the
      circle.</para>

      <para>'<code>DOT</code>' : The origin will be plotted as a dot and the
      wind shaft will start a short distance from the dot.</para>

      <para>'<code>OFF</code>' : The origin is not plotted but the wind shaft
      will start at the origin point.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="Wind_Flags_Calm_Indicator">
      <title>Calm Indicator</title>

      <para>According to the WMO standard, calm is indicated by a circle
      around the origin marker. If the parameter
      <parameter>WIND_FLAG_CALM_INDICATOR</parameter> is set to
      '<code>ON</code>' (default), a calm indicator will be plotted when
      plotting wind flags.</para>

      <para>The calm indicator can have different forms depending upon the
      <parameter>WIND_FLAG_ORIGIN_MARKER</parameter> parameter. If
      <parameter>WIND_FLAG_ORIGIN_MARKER</parameter> is set to
      '<code>CIRCLE</code>', then the calm indicator will be plotted as a
      circle around the origin circle. If
      <parameter>WIND_FLAG_ORIGIN_MARKER</parameter> is set to
      '<code>DOT</code>' , then the calm indicator will be plotted as a circle
      around a dot. If <parameter>WIND_FLAG_ORIGIN_MARKER</parameter> is set
      to '<code>OFF</code>' , then the calm indicator will also be plotted as
      a circle around a dot, as it is regarded as being necessary to show the
      exact location of the calm.</para>

      <para>The parameter <parameter>WIND_FLAG_CALM_INDICATOR_SIZE</parameter>
      controls the size of diameter of the calm indicator circle, the default
      being 0.3 centimetres. Control of the calm indicator size should be used
      to avoid congestion of wind symbols caused by the size of the users
      subpage and/or the map projection.</para>

      <remark>
        <para>Diagram 3</para>
      </remark>
    </section>

    <section id="Wind_Flags_Colour_and_Thickness">
      <title>Colour and Thickness</title>

      <para>The parameters <parameter>WIND_FLAG_THICKNESS</parameter> and
      <parameter>WIND_FLAG_COLOUR</parameter> are used to distinguish wind
      flag plotting from other wind fields in the same subpage.</para>

      <para>The parameter <parameter>WIND_FLAG_THICKNESS</parameter> will draw
      lines n times thicker than the default value. It will affect only the
      thickness of the wind flag shaft, not the barbs or pennants.</para>

      <para>The parameter <parameter>WIND_FLAG_COLOUR</parameter> controls the
      colour of the wind flags. Observe that only one colour at a time can be
      used to plot flags each time <function>PWIND</function> is
      called.</para>

      <para>The default value for <parameter>WIND_FLAG_THICKNESS</parameter>
      is <code>1</code> and the default colour for
      <parameter>WIND_FLAG_COLOUR</parameter> is '<code>BLUE</code>'.</para>
    </section>
  </section>



  <section id="Plotting_Wind_Arrows">
    <title>Plotting Wind Arrows</title>

    <para>A wind arrow is represented by a vector whose length and head size
    is proportional to the speed of the wind, and whose thickness remains
    constant (except for low wind speeds).</para>

    <para>The vector either starts at the exact location of the current grid
    point, or is centred on it. The orientation of the vector represents the
    direction of the wind.</para>

    <section id="Unit_Velocity">
      <title>Unit Velocity</title>

      <para><parameter>WIND_ARROW_UNIT_VELOCITY</parameter> is used to define
      the wind speed. A unit vector (1.0 cm) on the unscaled output plot
      represents the default value of 25 m/s.</para>

      <para>When <parameter>WIND_ARROW_UNIT_VELOCITY</parameter> is set to
      <code>0.0</code>, Magics will calculate the maximum wind speed for the
      geographical area requested and will use this maximum for the unit
      velocity. This means that the unit velocity will vary depending on the
      area being plotted.</para>

      <para>It should be noted that if a scaling factor is applied to the
      output plot using postprocessor or hardware scaling facilities, the unit
      length of the wind arrow will also be scaled by the same factor.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="Wind_Arrows_Plot_Suppression">
      <title>Plot Suppression</title>

      <para>To suppress the plotting of wind arrows above and below certain
      wind speed values, the parameters
      <parameter>WIND_ARROW_MAX_SPEED</parameter> and
      <parameter>WIND_ARROW_MIN_SPEED</parameter> may be used. The default
      values of these parameters are set to very high and very low values so
      that all wind speeds will be plotted. The suppression of wind arrows may
      be useful to isolate certain wind speeds or to plot them in a different
      style to other winds.</para>

      <!-- NOT IMPLEMENTED yet as of 19/01/2007
      <remark>
      <para>The parameter <parameter>WIND_ARROW_CROSS_BOUNDARY</parameter>
      controls the plotting of wind arrows on and outside the subpage
      boundary. It may be set to '<code>ON</code>' or '<code>OFF</code>' .
      When set to '<code>ON</code>' , which is the default, wind arrows are
      not plotted on or outside the boundary.</para>
      </remark>

      <remark>
        <para>Diagram 4</para>
      </remark>
      -->
    </section>

    <section id="Calm_Winds">
      <title>Calm Winds</title>

      <para>Generally, winds below 0.5 m/s are regarded as calm. The parameter
      <parameter>WIND_ARROW_CALM_BELOW</parameter> sets the upper limit for
      calm winds. The default value is <code>0.5</code>.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="Calm_Indicator">
      <title>Calm Indicator</title>

      <para>Calm winds may be plotted by setting the parameter
      <parameter>WIND_ARROW_CALM_INDICATOR</parameter> to '<code>ON</code>',
      default being '<code>OFF</code>'. These will be plotted by a circle
      round a dot, where the dot indicates the exact position of the current
      grid point.</para>

      <para>The parameter
      <parameter>WIND_ARROW_CALM_INDICATOR_SIZE</parameter> controls the size
      of the diameter of the calm indicator circle, default 0.3 centimetres.
      Control of the calm indicator size should be used to avoid congestion of
      wind symbols caused by the size of the users subpage and/or the map
      projection.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="Origin_Position">
      <title>Origin Position</title>

      <para>The Parameter <parameter>WIND_ARROW_ORIGIN_POSITION</parameter>
      places the wind arrows at different positions relative to the origin of
      the wind. It can take two values, '<code>TAIL</code>' or
      '<code>CENTRE</code>', the default being '<code>TAIL</code>'.</para>

      <para>'<code>TAIL</code>' : The tails of the arrows will be plotted at
      the origin points of the wind.</para>

      <para>'<code>CENTRE</code>' : The centre points of the wind arrows will
      be plotted at the origin points.</para>

      <para>The position of the origin will be indicated in the wind arrow
      legend by a cross.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="Wind_Arrow_Colour">
      <title>Colour</title>

      <para>Wind arrow colour is set by the parameter
      <parameter>WIND_ARROW_COLOUR</parameter> (default
      '<code>BLUE</code>').</para>
    </section>

    <section id="Arrow_Thickness">
      <title>Arrow Thickness</title>

      <para>The thickness of wind arrow shafts can be controlled by the
      parameter <parameter>WIND_ARROW_THICKNESS</parameter>, the value of
      which defaults to <code>1</code>.</para>

      <para>As the size of the arrow head is proportional to the overall
      length of the arrow, it is possible, in the case of low wind speeds,
      that the height of the arrow head may grow smaller than the thickness of
      the shaft. Magics prevents this from happening by examining the ratio of
      the height of the arrow head to the thickness of the shaft for all
      arrows whose length is less than that of the unit vector. Thus if the
      arrow head height falls below three times the shaft thickness, the shaft
      thickness is said to have violated the arrow head. When violation
      occurs, Magics will reduce the shaft thickness so that it is exactly one
      third of the arrow head height.</para>

      <para>The shaft thickness will remain constant, at the user specified or
      default value, for all arrows whose length is greater than that of the
      unit vector.</para>

      <remark>
        <para>Diagram 5</para>
      </remark>
    </section>

    <section id="Arrow_Head_Style">
      <title>Arrow Head Style</title>

      <important> <title>Magics++</title>
      <productname>Magics++</productname> uses an easier
      system of specifying arrow head styles than previous versions.
      The old parameter,
      <parameter>WIND_ARROW_HEAD_INDEX</parameter>, is still
      supported but is now deprecated.</important>

      <para></para>

      <para>Wind arrow heads can be configured through two parameters:
      <parameter>WIND_ARROW_HEAD_SHAPE</parameter> (integer from 0 to 3) and
      <parameter>WIND_ARROW_HEAD_RATIO</parameter> (real from 0 to 1). The
      first of these parameters specifies which type of head the wind arrow
      will have, and the second specifies the ratio of the width
      of the arrow head compared to its length. The following diagram
      illustrates the effect of these parameters:</para>

      <figure id="figure_wind_arrow_heads">
        <title>Wind Arrow Heads</title>
        <mediaobject id="wind_arrow_heads_diagram">
            <imageobject role="fo">
              <imagedata fileref="../diagrams/diagram_wind_arrow_heads_01.png"
                         format="PNG" width="8cm" depth="8cm"  align="center" />
            </imageobject>

            <imageobject role="html">
              <imagedata fileref="images/diagrams/diagram_wind_arrow_heads_01.png"
                         format="PNG" align="center" />
            </imageobject>
         </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>


    <section id="Wind_Arrow_Legend">
      <title>Wind Arrow Legend</title>

      <para>A wind arrow legend box containing a plot of a unit vector and its
      unit value will be plotted, by default, in the upper right hand corner
      of the page, just outside the subpage.</para>

      <para>The attributes colour, line style, thickness and arrowhead style
      of the unit vector will be the same as for wind arrows plotted in the
      subpage. The frame of the wind arrow legend box will be plotted with the
      same attributes as the subpage frame.</para>

      <para>By default, the legend will be plotted just outside the top right
      hand corner of the subpage. The wind arrow legend box may be placed in
      any position within the user's page using the
      <parameter>WIND_ARROW_LEGEND_X_POSITION</parameter> and
      <parameter>WIND_ARROW_LEGEND_Y_POSITION</parameter> parameters to define
      the position of the lower left hand corner of the wind arrow legend
      box.</para>

      <para>The size of the legend is controlled by the two parameters
      <parameter>WIND_ARROW_LEGEND_X_LENGTH</parameter> and
      <parameter>WIND_ARROW_LEGEND_Y_LENGTH</parameter> , whose values default
      to 1.2cm and 0.6cm respectively.</para>

      <para>To request blanking behind the legend box, the parameter
      <parameter>WIND_ARROW_LEGEND_BLANKING</parameter> may be set to
      '<code>ON</code>', the default
      being '<code>OFF</code>'. Blanking is only effective when the legend is
      partially or totally inside the subpage. To obtain full blanking, the
      action routine <function>PWIND</function> should be called before any
      other action routines.</para>

      <para>To suppress the plotting of the wind arrow legend box, the
      parameter <parameter>WIND_ARROW_LEGEND</parameter> should be set to
      '<code>OFF</code>', the default being '<code>ON</code>' .</para>

      <para>The wind arrow legend may also be plotted by the general legend
      drawing facilities in Magics. This can be achieved by setting the
      parameter <parameter>LEGEND</parameter> to '<code>ON</code>' before
      calling <function>PWIND</function>. When this is required,
      <parameter>WIND_ARROW_LEGEND</parameter> should be set to
      '<code>OFF</code>' to avoid having the arrow legend drawn twice.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <xi:include href="../paramtables/pwind_tables.xml"
              xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

  <xi:include href="../paramtables/Wind_wind_magml_tables.xml"
              xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

  <xi:include href="../paramtables/Wind_wind_magml_flat_tables.xml"
              xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />


  <section id="Wind_Program_Examples">
    <title>Program Examples</title>

    <para>The following examples illustrate the plotting of wind.</para>

  </section>

  <xi:include href="../examples/manual/xml/wind_examples.xml"
          xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

</chapter>
